<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks on some late sermons, and in particular on Dr. Sherlock's sermon at the Temple, Decemb. 30, 1694 in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2124</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12307105</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12307105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 639:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks on some late sermons, and in particular on Dr. Sherlock's sermon at the Temple, Decemb. 30, 1694 in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, with additions ; together with a letter to the author of a pamphlet, entitled, A defence of the Archbishop's sermon, &amp;c. and several other sermons, &amp;c.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[12], 52 [i.e. 53] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A defence of the Archbishops sermon ..." has been erroneously attributed to Thomas Wagstaffe. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712. --  Defence of the Archbishop's sermon.</term>
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Sermon preached at the Temple-Church, December 30, 1694.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59293:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REMARKS ON SOME <hi>Late Sermons;</hi> And in particular On Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Sermon at the <hi>Temple, Decemb.</hi> 30. 1694.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter to a Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Edition, with Additions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a Letter to the Author of a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, entitled, <hi>A Defence of the Archbiſhop</hi>'s <hi>Sermon,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And ſeveral other Sermons,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:59293:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59293:2"/>
            <head>To the AUTHOR of the DEFENCE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have read over your Pamphlet called <hi>a Defence,</hi> &amp;c. and I give you my moſt <hi>hearty Thanks</hi> for it. This, I know, you will look upon as an unſuitable return for thoſe Characters you have ſo liberally beſtowed on me, of <hi>Scribler, Libeller, Villain, Cerberus, Lyar:</hi> And not content with theſe, out of your abundant Charity have cloathed them with very improving and ſignificant Epithets, as <hi>black mouth'd</hi> Libeller, <hi>black mouth'd</hi> Cerberus, <hi>barbarous</hi> Lyar, and abundance more of the ſame Strain in every Page; whereby you have opened the inſide of your Heart, and convinc'd me of your good Inclinations to me-ward, however unworthy, and undeſerving. Alas! Sir, that a Gentleman of your Parts ſhould have loſt ſo much Time, as after the ſpending many Years in Liberal Studies, ſhould at laſt arrive only to ſuch a Degree of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as a Man of an ordinary Capacity would, in one Hours time, be compleatly Maſter of in the Converſe and Education of <hi>Billingſgate:</hi> Had you been pleaſed to have beſtowed your good Graces on me, in the Language of a Gentleman, or a Scholar, or in any other beſides that of Scavengers and Car-men, I ſhould have taken it every Jot as well; but every Man in his own way. In the mean time give me leave to tell you, That though you have taken abundance of Pains, and ſaid your utmoſt in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you could, yet all your Labour is perfectly loſt: For the World is given to judge with their own Eyes; and they will not take the Character of the <hi>Remarks,</hi> or of the Author of it, from any Thing that you ſay, but from the Book it ſelf. And if (to come out of your Debt) I ſhould ſay you were a <hi>Fine, Civil, Well-bred Gentleman,</hi> it will not turn to your Advantage; for no Body will believe it, who hath read but four Lines of your Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet. And therefore you may ſay all the bad Things you can think on, and I may return them in as many good ones; yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you nor I ſhall fare the better, or the worſe for it: But it will be the reſpective Pamphlets which at laſt muſt determine, who is the <hi>Scribler,</hi> the <hi>Libeller,</hi> the <hi>Villain,</hi> the <hi>Lyar,</hi> and ſo forth. When therefore theſe laudable Qualities are brought to the Touchſtone, and tryed by the Subject Matter of the Two Books, the Reader will never ask your leave to aſſign them to the Right Owner: For
<pb facs="tcp:59293:3"/>
though indeed he is purely beholding to you for theſe goodly Terms, yet the Application of them is intirely in him; and he will be ſure to adjudge them to him that beſt deſerves them.</p>
            <p>And this Sir, is all the Anſwer you are to expect from me to all thoſe fair ſpoken Titles you have given me under what Form ſoever; that is, to half your Book. But I hold my ſelf bound to account to you for ſome further Favours wherewith you have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged me, and to lay before you the Grounds why I returned you my <hi>hearty Thanks:</hi> For though 'tis poſſible you might not deſign me any Kindneſs, and conſequently might not expect any Thanks from me, being conſcious to your ſelf that you never intended to give me Occaſion; but I do not ſtand upon theſe Niceties, nor will examin your Intentions, when you have given Matter for a Man's Gratitude to work upon. And I do aſſure you, That both you, and your Pamphlet, have very well deſerved of me, whether you intended it or no: And accordingly I am reſolved to be Thankful to you, whether you will or no, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You have effectually convinc'd me (and the World too, ſo far as your Pamphlet hath been taken Notice of) of the Hatred and ill Will you bear me, for the <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>plain Truths</hi> delivered in my Book, which I very much rejoice at, well knowing that it will tend to my Reputation amongſt all honeſt and ſober Men; and (to deal plainly with you) I hope I ſhall never deſerve your good Opinion; and nothing can gratify me more than to be ill ſpoken of by you, and ſuch as you; the harder your Words are, the greater Honour and Kindneſs you do me: And my poor Pamphlet hath <hi>now</hi> one Character more to recommend it to the World, That Men of your Temper are very wrathful and diſpleaſed at it. Your <hi>Villain, Cerbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and <hi>Lyar,</hi> are Titles of Honour and Eſteem, and (when they come from your Mouth) will ſerve inſtead of ſo many ſtudied and elaborate Commendations <hi>in Laudem Authoris.</hi> 'Tis Panegyrick in maſquerade, the moſt real Kindneſs a little diſguiſed and rough clad; for all the World will conclude, That the Truths are very clear and evident, when they ſee you ſo much provoked, and your <hi>Gall</hi> and <hi>Spleen</hi> affected in ſo high a Degree; as when the <hi>Sun ſhines</hi> brighteſt, the <hi>Dunghill ſtinks</hi> moſt. I pray, Sir, ſpare me that one <hi>Alluſion,</hi> 'tis all the trouble I am like to give you for your <hi>Animals,</hi> your <hi>Poiſons,</hi> your <hi>Bumpers, Kennels, Kidneys,</hi> and ſuch like Flights of your Wit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You have hereby given me a juſt Occaſion of Reprinting the <hi>Remarks,</hi> which I now do under a new Capacity, as a <hi>direct Anſwer</hi> and <hi>perfect Confutation</hi> of your <hi>Defence;</hi> and, as ſuch, I ſhall leave it to the Judgment of every impartial and unprejudiced Reader. For
<pb facs="tcp:59293:3"/>
if any Man, either of Senſe or Honeſty, can think that you have ſaid any Thing to weaken the Force, or invalidate the Truth of any one Paragraph or Sentence in it, I am contented to join iſſue with you, and to own, That it is as mean a <hi>Scrible</hi> as ever came from the Preſs; for (to ſpeak plain truth) that muſt be very <hi>mean</hi> indeed, which ſuch a <hi>Defence</hi> as yours is able to impair or diſcredit. And I am ſo little concern'd in any Thing you have ſaid, that had it not been for a much better End, <hi>viz.</hi> The making the <hi>Remarks</hi> more Publick; you and your <hi>Defence</hi> might have lain long enough, before I could think either worth the taking Notice of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You have taken abundance of Pains, and ſaid all that you are able, to juſtify one of the main Charges laid down in the <hi>Remarks;</hi> that is, <hi>To blacken all they can whom they think are not in their ungodly Intereſt, or obſtruct it.</hi> This Sir, I thank you, you have abundantly prov'd, and made good, beyond Exception. And let any Man read your Pamphlet, and then doubt of the Truth of this, if he can; it was kindly done of you to confirm my Allegations with freſh Inſtances of your own, and to accumulate new Proofs from one end of your Book to the other. For your <hi>Satyr</hi> is every jot as Fierce and Furious, only a little more <hi>Dirty,</hi> and ſeems as if it was bred in a <hi>Pigſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I am yet further obliged to you for confirming (according to your Model and Talent) all other Matters and Things in the <hi>Remarks</hi> you have thought good to take Notice of; ſo that, if you had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, you might have called your Pamphlet a <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Remarks:</hi> For I can aſſure you, it is a much better Defence of the <hi>Remarks,</hi> than of the <hi>Sermons.</hi> This, I ſuppoſe, you did not think on, and it may be you do not yet know it; but in this I ſhall relieve you by an enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Particulars, and then take my leave of you.</p>
            <p n="1">I. You tell me, (p. 1.) That I charge <hi>ſuch of the Clergy as think themſelves oblig'd to ſpeak honorably of the preſent Government with incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency with their former Principles and Practices;</hi> and then add, <hi>If it could be but as well proved, as it is boldly aſſerted.</hi> Well, Sir, whether I have proved it or no, I ſhall leave to the Reader; but I am very certain you have proved it ſufficiently: For you immediately tell me, I ſhould <hi>have conſider'd what hath been writ in defence of the Clergy from that Charge, by Mr.</hi> Johnſon, <hi>and the Author of</hi> Bibliotheca Politica. This Sir, let me tell you, is a very lucky Choice, and you could not have pickt out two ſuch Authors for my Purpoſe. For the Principles that both of <hi>Them</hi> proceed upon, are directly <hi>contrary</hi> to thoſe which the Gentlemen (whom the <hi>Remarks</hi> charges with inconſiſtency) have aſſerted, preached, and maintained over and over: Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> and the <hi>Letter to the Lord Ruſſel</hi> conſiſt like Fire and Water, and Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>'s
<pb facs="tcp:59293:4"/>
               <hi>Dialogues</hi> and the <hi>Bibliotheca</hi> are as conſiſtent as Contradictions, or as that Doctor is conſiſtent with himſelf; ſo that you defend them from inconſiſtency by plainly proving it: For if theſe Gentlemen ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify their preſent Practices by the Principles of thoſe two Authors, then they do it by deſerting and abandoning their own Principles, and that, Sir, (with your good leave) is <hi>Inconſiſtency</hi> with a Witneſs, and if you pleaſe down-right <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> But you tell us, they defend them from inconſiſtency by proving, That <hi>Paſſive Obedience, as cry'd up in the late Times, was never the Doctrin of the Church of</hi> England: But by your Favour, that is more than they, or you, or all your Party, are able to prove; but that is not the Queſtion now, and therefore ſuppoſe it, what is that to the Purpoſe? Theſe very Gentlemen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and taught, That Paſſive Obedience was the Doctrin of that Church, and as ſuch preſſed it upon the Conſciences of Men under pain of Damnation. And does not your own Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> tell one of them, (Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>) That <hi>he cram'd Paſſive Obedience down the Throat of a dying Lord?</hi> And could you find no Body but Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him from Inconſiſtency? And I'll warrant you Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> is defended from Inconſiſtency too, by his old Friend Mr. <hi>Johnſon.</hi> Sir, you have the ſtrangeſt way of defending Things that ever was heard of: But it ſeems even this Defence (ſuch as it is) admits of Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for you add, <hi>For ſuch of them as might be hurried into that Opinion, by the Current of the Times;</hi> meaning St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> Dr. <hi>Patrick,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> and all the Eccleſiaſtical Champions of the Uſurpation; (for theſe are the Men who held this Opinion are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with Inconſiſtency, and whom you undertake to defend from it:) Theſe, it ſeems, are the light and inconſiderate Men, who took up an Opinion of this Weight with haſte and precipitation, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due Regard had to the Nature of it. So that when Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> wrot the <hi>Letter to the Lord Ruſſel,</hi> when Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> wrot his <hi>Dialogues,</hi> Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi> his <hi>Friendly Debate</hi> and <hi>Paraphraſes,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> his <hi>Caſe of Reſiſtance,</hi> Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> his <hi>Jeſuits Loyalty;</hi> 'twas all Weakneſs and Incogitancy, they ſwam with the Stream, without either Caution or Conſideration. Now, Sir, if this is all that can be honeſtly ſaid for them, 'tis ſure no extraordinary Character, and makes their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of no Value in the World. For if Men can be hurried into ſuch Opinions, by the Current of the Times, who knows but they may be ſo ſtill? And the wiſeſt Man living will never be able to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, whether their new Opinions and Practices are the reſult of their Judgments, or the effects of the Times; and give me leave to tell you, That when Men change their Doctrins, with Seaſons and Opportunities, 'tis a ſhrewd Suſpition that the <hi>Times</hi> make the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines;
<pb facs="tcp:59293:4"/>
and if you will derive their Pedigree, they may ſay to the <hi>Revolution, Thou art our Father.</hi> However <hi>ſuch</hi> it ſeems they are, and what is to be ſaid to defend <hi>them?</hi> Why as to that, you tell us, <hi>It may be reply'd that no Man is forbid to examin his Principles.</hi> To examin his Principles? No doubt of it. But pray, Sir, what do you mean by <hi>Examining?</hi> One would think that when Men preach <hi>Sermons,</hi> write Books, treat of the Queſtion <hi>ex Profeſſo,</hi> that they either had, or at leaſt ought to have <hi>examined</hi> them. Upon my Word you make rare Men of them, and fit to be truſted with our Conſciences. And this is a glorious <hi>Defence</hi> indeed, that from Year to Year, from Sermon to Sermon, from Book to Book, they inculcate theſe Principles, and faſten them upon the Conſciences of Men, as eternal and immutable Doctrines, and yet never <hi>examined</hi> them themſelves. Sir, this is a lamentable Caſe, and you are very hard put to it, when you have no other way to defend them, but what at one Daſh blaſts all their Authority, and diſcredits every Thing they have ſaid ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution as well as before: For I crave leave to tell you, That meer <hi>Swearing</hi> will never mend a Man's Character. And therefore you call upon them to much purpoſe, <hi>to lay hold on all Occaſions to commend the preſent Government;</hi> when at the ſame time you have taken extraordinary Care that their Words ſhall go for juſt nothing: For if the World believe you, I am certain they neither will, nor can believe them. But for all that, they muſt be defended. And you yet add, That <hi>my whole Charge amounts to no more than this, that ſome of the Clergy were formerly Blind, but now they See.</hi> Well! if my Charge amounts to no more, yours (you ſee) amounts to a great deal more; and you muſt anſwer for it as well as you can. However methinks this is a pretty way to defend them from <hi>Inconſiſtency;</hi> for what you call <hi>Blindneſs</hi> and <hi>Seeing,</hi> I call <hi>Owning</hi> and <hi>Renouncing,</hi> and ſo does all the World beſides: But you may call it what you pleaſe, your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors mean the ſame Thing; and the plain Engliſh is, They have forſaken their former Principles, and that is the <hi>Inconſiſtency</hi> I charge them with, which you frankly own, and abundantly prove; ſo that as far as I can ſee, we are perfectly agreed, and there need no more Words about it.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The next Thing is the Diſtinction of the Clergy, between the <hi>Sycophants and Flatterers, who deify the Uſurpation,</hi> and thoſe who comply, yet retain their old Principles, and are far the <hi>Beſt, the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, the Honeſteſt, and moſt Numerous.</hi> This, Sir, is a Truth I do not expect you ſhould own; but for all that you cannot forbear implying it by your <hi>Threatning:</hi> For you think I ought to have kept this as an <hi>importent Secret</hi> under <hi>ſacred Concealment, leſt the Government be on their
<pb facs="tcp:59293:5"/>
Guard againſt them, and either put their Loyalty to the Touchſtone, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them abjure, as his been done in</hi> Scotland, <hi>or take ſuch other Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as may turn them all out, and make room for honeſter Men.</hi> And why did not you alſo tell us here, and <hi>turn them all out</hi> as he did in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> Why becauſe you are a cunning Man, and will not tell your <hi>Secrets,</hi> leſt the Church ſhould have been on her Guard, and look to themſelves, that they are not enſnared by one who hath given ſuch evident Indications of his good Will towards them: And ſince we are upon <hi>Secrets,</hi> I do not much care if I tell you another Secret. <q>A good number of <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Divines in <hi>Scotland</hi> (who had taken the Oaths) were turned out by the Aſſembly, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Churches fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led with honeſt <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> without the leaſt Allowance from their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings: Whereupon they petitioned <hi>your Great and Illuſtrious</hi> for a Maintenance out of the depriv'd Biſhops Revenues, which he had ſeiz'd upon. Now, Sir, out of his abundant Charity, heroick Nature, and great Affections to the Church, he allowed them not one Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: And yet notwithſtanding he actually gives a Penſion of 1200 <hi>l. per An.</hi> to <hi>Presbyteterian</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> Miniſters in the Province of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in <hi>April</hi> laſt ſigned Privy Seals for the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Payment of it; and for the Proof of this, you may, if you pleaſe, conſult the <hi>Letters Mandat</hi> in the <hi>Signet Office.</hi>
               </q> Sir, I doubt you muſt <hi>reverſe</hi> your Character, and make the Clergy <hi>now</hi> ſtark <hi>Blind,</hi> if they do not <hi>ſee</hi> upon what Terms they ſtand with your renowned Deliverer, and what great and glorious Deſigns he hath to devour them, ſo ſoon as he hath Power and Opportunity. Your Example of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Project of <hi>Abjuration,</hi> and <hi>turning all out,</hi> hath been upon the Anvil, and he hath as good a Will to the Church Lands as to his Father's Crown: But he never durſt put it to the Iſſue, leſt it ſhould diſcover the Weakneſs of his Intereſt. For (to give you one <hi>Secret</hi> more) the Eyes of the Nation are opened, they ſee themſelves cheated and abuſed, and inſtead of Liberties and Privileges, find themſelves made Tools to inſatiable Ambition, and a Morſel for execrable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide. And it was the moſt unaccountable Infatuation to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected otherwiſe; that he, who had Stomach enough to devour his Father, would ever ſtick at preying on the Wealth, the Rights, and Vitals of a Nation. I know, Sir, you have a Remedy for all this, and you will tell me, it had been Wiſdom to have put this under <hi>ſacred Concealment,</hi> leſt the Government guard it ſelf againſt the People, and ſerve them as the <hi>de Witts</hi> were ſerved in <hi>Holland;</hi> that is, to knock them on the Head to make room for the Loyal and Honeſt <hi>Dutch.</hi> And then, Sir, your Deliverance would be compleat.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:59293:5"/>III. I had honeſtly told you, That <hi>all the Liberty this Nation enjoys under this Revolution, is a Liberty of giving</hi> 7 <hi>or</hi> 8 <hi>Millions yearly,</hi> &amp;c. and defied all the <hi>Flatterers</hi> to ſhew any other Liberty, beſides ſuch as they, as the <hi>direct and immediate Fruits of the Revolution.</hi> I pray, Sir, mark the laſt Words, for upon <hi>them</hi> all the matter depends; for there are ſeveral Liberties an <hi>Engliſh man</hi> enjoys which are general, and not appropriate to Times and Seaſons. As for Inſtance, an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> may breath in the <hi>Engliſh Air,</hi> without being beholding to any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: but to have that Air polluted by execrable <hi>Oaths, Perjuries,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> this is peculiar to the Revolution. It is the Privilege of the ſeveral Societies of Merchants to trade abroad to the reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Places and Kingdoms; but to have this Trade crampt by a <hi>Dutch</hi> Intereſt, to have their Effects taken, and themſelves ruin'd, this is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Revolution. It is the Liberty of any Man to refuſe had Mony; but to have nothing elſe but bad Mony to refuſe, is the direct Effect of the Revolution. Any Man has Liberty to go about his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Occaſions on Sundays; but to have Licenſed Coaches to carry them is purely owing to the Revolution. It is the Privilege of the City of <hi>London</hi> to have Coals from <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> but to have them at 5 <hi>l.</hi> a Chaldron, and moreover 5 <hi>s.</hi> a Chaldron Tax, this is the peculiar Liberty of the Revolution: So that, Sir, if you carefully diſtinguiſh this Point, you and I ſhall ſoon be agreed. As to inſtance in ſome of tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Liberties you reckon up as the <hi>direct Fruits of the Revolution. We are</hi> (ſay you) <hi>now at Liberty to make ſuch Laws as are proper to preſerve us from Dangers.</hi> Very well, Sir; but you forget to add, That we are in the greateſt <hi>Danger</hi> from the <hi>Law-makers</hi> themſelves; and that we are at Liberty to purchaſe any Law with our Money, provided we will go to the Price of it. Again, <hi>All Proteſtants have now a Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> yea Sir, and a Liberty too to have <hi>no Conſcience</hi> at all. You add, <hi>We are now deliver'd from impos'd Sheriffs, and packt Juries;</hi> yes, by all means, and from ſuborn'd and perjur'd Witneſſes, as in the Caſes of <hi>Young, Blacket, Lunt Womble,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We are now deliver'd from all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreints of voting for Members of Parliament;</hi> yea, Sir, and from all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreint too of voting for Members to no Parliament at all. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> no fear of having a Court Faction impos'd on us as the Repreſentatives of the Nation;</hi> eſpecially conſidering that there are no above 350 in the Houſe, who are Officers or Penſioners <hi>We are now ſecured againſt keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a ſtanding Army in Times of Peace;</hi> yes, Sir, and for a very good Reaſon, becauſe we have not had one Moments of <hi>Peace</hi> ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, nor are ever like to have it, to try the Experiment. <hi>We are now deliver'd from all Danger of being engag'd in a War with our Proteſtant
<pb facs="tcp:59293:6"/>
Allies the Dutch;</hi> I marry, Sir, this is a Liberty indeed, and worth all the reſt: But I wonder you ſhould be ſo ſhort, and not add, That we had now a Liberty of giving them 600000 <hi>l.</hi> at once, and three times as much at ſeveral other times; beſides the loſs of ten times more, by their clipping and embaſing our Coin, and ſupplanting and ruining our Trade.</p>
            <p>Theſe, Sir, and a great many more (with which you fill a Page and a half) I am reſolved never to Diſpute with you about; but only deſire you carefully to diſtinguiſh what are the proper and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Effects of the Revolution: And I dare promiſe you, you will confirm every Word I have ſaid, and upon the Foot of the Account you will find nothing but <hi>Iniquity, Fraud, and Beggary,</hi> entail'd upon the Nation; which you, if you pleaſe, may call glorious Liberties and Privileges. But every Man that can but remember for Ten years, and hath Eyes in his Head to compare the preſent State of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with what it was then, will not need your Inſtruction to ſee the Difference, and to point out the Authors of all and every one of theſe irrecoverable Calamities we now groan under.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. I had ſaid, That the Revolution (in the firſt Steps of it) was as great a Violation of Leagues and ſolemn Treaties, and the publick Faith of Nations, as ever was known; For that it was not only contrary to that perfect Peace and Amity that was then between K. <hi>James,</hi> and the <hi>States;</hi> but alſo contrary to their expreſs Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to his Ambaſſador in the very Caſe. Now, Sir, this you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack moſt terribly and furiouſly, (p. 9.) as in the firſt Place you ſay, <hi>The States made no War upon</hi> England, <hi>but only lent their Forces to the Prince of</hi> Orange: No, not at all, Sir; becauſe the Forces were all theirs, all the time under their Pay, and becauſe they received 600000 <hi>l.</hi> for the Expedition. This makes it a plain Caſe, that the <hi>States</hi> had nothing to do in the matter; and that they, honeſt Men, kept their Faith all the while inviolably with the King: Even as when the <hi>Dutch</hi> deny'd themſelves to be Chriſtians in <hi>India,</hi> and cut the Throats of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> why, Sir, they only <hi>lent</hi> themſelves to the <hi>Infidels,</hi> and they were the Murtherers, though it was committed by <hi>Dutch</hi> hands. Well, no Body knows the Advantage of a good Advocate: However you add, <hi>Though they had declared the War in their own Names, 'tis no more than what might be juſtified:</hi> Yes, moſt certainly; becauſe they not only did not <hi>declare</hi> it, but <hi>declared</hi> moſt ſolemnly and expreſly the clean contrary. But no matter for that, you ſtill go on, <hi>Though neither the Prince nor States had any Cauſe of their own, it would have been not only juſt but generous, to have lent
<pb facs="tcp:59293:6"/>
their helping hand to a neigbbouring Proteſtant Church and State.</hi> With all doubt, Sir, it is a great Argument of <hi>Dutch</hi> Juſtice and Generoſity, to invade a neighbouring Prince in perfect Peace with them; and at the ſame time to aſſure his Ambaſſador they had no Deſigns againſt him. Theſe, Sir, are terrible Demonſtrations, and who can ſay any Thing againſt them; but methinks you might have uſed your Victory a little more moderately. Was it not enough to confound your Adverſary by ſuch thundering Arguments, but you muſt over and above call him <hi>Lyar,</hi> and <hi>Villain,</hi> and <hi>Cerberus</hi> beſides? In the mean time, Sir, the Queſtion here (if you have not forget it) is not about <hi>Cauſes,</hi> and <hi>helping Hands,</hi> but concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>breach of Faith,</hi> and of <hi>ſolemn Leagues</hi> and <hi>Treaties:</hi> If therefore your <hi>Proteſtant Allies</hi> had a mind to <hi>help</hi> one of themſelves to cut the Throat of his Father, why let them do it; for being <hi>Dutch</hi> no Body expected otherwiſe from them. But what need they, at the ſame time, aſſure the old Gentleman, That they meant him no harm, but all the kindneſs in the World? If they had reſolved to aſſiſt ſome neighbouring <hi>Rebels,</hi> why they may do as they pleaſe, 'tis but acting like themſelves: But to do this while they were under the Bond of <hi>Leagues</hi> and <hi>Treaties,</hi> and preſent <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Aſſurances</hi> to the contrary; This Sir, by your Favour, is a little too much even for our <hi>Proteſtant Allies,</hi> who notwithſtanding may be allowed as much in ſuch Caſes, as any People in the World. What tragical Work do you make with the <hi>French King</hi>'s deſtroying Towns <hi>after ſurrender, upon the Faith of Articles?</hi> (p. 14.) As to the Truth of which however I deſire to be excuſed; for I doubt your Authors, <hi>Monſieur Obſervator</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Gazette,</hi> are not of much Credit. But I pray, Sir, is the <hi>Faith of Articles</hi> more Sacred than the <hi>Faith of Leagues,</hi> or the <hi>Faith of ſolemn Aſſurances to Ambaſſadors?</hi> Now if violating the <hi>Faith of Articles</hi> renders a Prince (who is not of our ſide) Ten times worſe than <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and all the <hi>Savages</hi> and <hi>Barbarous</hi> in Nature? Pray what a goodly Figure will your <hi>Stadtholder,</hi> with all his <hi>Dutch Proteſtants</hi> behind him, make when they appear in Stor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, breaking through all the Bonds of <hi>Nature, Religion, common Honeſty, and the Faith of Nations?</hi> I doubt, Sir, (let you and I do what we can) the Revolution, with all its Circumſtances, will ſtand upon Record, as the moſt perfidious and treacherous Piece of Villany that ever was, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ever will be in the World.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, it were very eaſy for me to go through every Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph of your Pamphlet; and to ſhew in particular how obliging
<pb facs="tcp:59293:7"/>
you have been to me, in confirming and illuſtrating the <hi>Truth</hi> of all that I have inſiſted on. It muſt be acknowledged, Sir, that you have given the <hi>Remarks</hi> all the Reputation that you are able: And if any Man doubted of any Part or Branch of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I do not queſtion but by your Book they have received abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Satisfaction. But I cannot ſtay to enumerate all your Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations: I hope this little will be ſufficient for the teſtifying my Reſpects to you; and I fear a great deal too much for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's Excuſe and Pardon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59293:7"/>
            <head>REMARKS, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU tell me that <hi>Dyer</hi>'s News-Letter was the firſt that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d you with the <hi>Reverend Dean</hi>'s Sermon; That the Character he gives it, and the <hi>Fine Strokes</hi> he ſays were in it, tempted you to buy it, and read it: That now having read it, you very much <hi>admire</hi> it, and deſire my Opinion concerning it, which I ſhall frankly give you.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Place, I do perfectly Concur with you, and <hi>admire</hi> it too; though at the ſame time, it may be, I may as perfectly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree with you upon the Grounds and Reaſons for which I admire it. For this ſame <hi>Admiration</hi> hath ſeveral different, nay contrary Objects: Any Thing that is Extraordinary either for its <hi>Excellency,</hi> or its <hi>Meaneſs;</hi> any <hi>fine Strokes</hi> of Truth, or Untruth; any Thing that is highly Agreeable, or highly Unſuitable to the Character of the Perſons ſpeaking, or ſpoken of, may equally move this Paſſion. There was a Time when ſober and ſerious Men uſed to <hi>admire</hi> to ſee Divines ſay and unſay, and contradict themſelves, as faſt as they write; but that <hi>Wonder</hi> is of late much abated by its frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And therefore 'tis poſſible you may admire the Dean's Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance in one Senſe, and I in another; though we both may <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> it. However, what ſeems to me to be of that Strein you ſhall have preſently, and then (if you pleaſe) you may compare it with your own Judgment; and if I have not the Luck to jump exactly with you in all Things, I think, notwithſtanding that, I ſhall deliver the Senſe of above three Parts of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But before I enter upon the immediate Subject, The Dean's <hi>ſingle Sermon;</hi> it may not be amiſs a little to reflect on the Stile of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Sermons, which will be no Digreſſion, but a proper Preface and Introduction to what follows. Now Sermons, Sir, you know are, or ought to be, very ſerious Things; and when Men are ſuppoſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59293:8"/>
to ſpeak the Mind of God to the People, and to direct their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, they ought to confine themſelves to the Rules of ſtrict and ſober Truth. Laviſh and extravagant Expreſſions, and the Liberty of <hi>Poets</hi> and <hi>Orators,</hi> very ill become the Character of thoſe who Serve at the Altar: And (however ſome may Pride themſelves in it) it equally diſhonours God, and ſhames their Profeſſion. But this Practice is never worſe, and more fulſom, than when the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of it is <hi>frail and fallible</hi> Man? And when they find, or make Occaſion to diſcourſe of <hi>Men</hi> in their Sermons, one would think the ſubject Matter ſhould teach them Moderation and Temperance, Decorum and Decency. For Man is a <hi>weak, wilful, peeviſh, and proud Creature;</hi> and when they ſee thoſe Qualities Deify'd by vile and paltry Encomiums, every Man who hath Eyes in his Head ſees through it, and laughs at it. <hi>Men</hi> are known well enough, and their Vices notorious; and it is not all the Harangues of a pert Flatterer that can make Men believe one Word of it, no more than he believes it himſelf. A little Diſcretion, without any other Vertue, would be apt to teach Men Caution on this Account: For the World is mutable, and the many Changes which we have ſeen with our Eyes make it not impoſſible but there may be one more; and it would be a terrible piece of Mortification, that theſe Men muſt be forced to Cry down what they now haſtily Cry up; to tranſlate their <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Phoenix's,</hi> into <hi>Tigers</hi> and <hi>Birds of Prey.</hi> But Men of limber and pliable Conſciences can eaſily do this; and the ſame Topicks, and Common Places (where there is no Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour nor Conſcience to ſuit them to their proper Subjects) will fit all Caſes, and Panegyricks, and Eulogies, and Satyrs, and Invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, will agree to the ſame Subjects and Perſons if there be <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> in the Caſe, and as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> wiſely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,<note n="(a)">Pref. to the Caſe of Allegiance.</note> 
               <hi>No Man is forbid to grow wiſer.</hi> I know, Sir, you have heard of a certain Perſon that was to have a Statue made; the Statuary ſaid, That he had the Statue of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and it was but putting a new Head to it, and it would do very well: And juſt ſo are theſe Men's Encomiums; the glorious Epithets of <hi>Illuſtrious, Deliverer, Saviour,</hi> if the Tide turns may be Cap'd with <hi>Barbarous, Unnatural, Deſtroyer.</hi> Alas! Sir, it is the ſame Man ſtill, the Difference only lies in a few Words, which mean nothing, nor never were intended to mean any thing. And I will venture all the Skill I have in Men, That there is not one of theſe Men who are now ſo fluſh with their Oratory, but, if the Scene alters, will change their Note too, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59293:8"/>
load their new Saint with all the hard Names they can think of: For Words, you know, are voluble Things; and if a Man hath a Stock of them (if there be not a ſteddy Principle to guide them) they will fly out upon all Occaſions, and ſerve all Purpoſes. And ſo, Sir, if you pleaſe, you may transfer the Alluſion of the <hi>Statue</hi> hither alſo; he will be the ſame Man ſtill, only his <hi>Mouth</hi> will be a little alter'd. He was an Artiſt that made a Picture which upon a ſmall turn was both an <hi>Angel</hi> and a <hi>Devil;</hi> but he was not the only Artiſt: For you ſhall ſee the ſame Thing done over again by the <hi>Grave,</hi> the <hi>Judicious,</hi> the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> (as they call one another) Turn the Picture to one Side, to the Side of the <hi>Sun,</hi> with Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity and Greatneſs on the back of it, and 'tis an <hi>Angel,</hi> a <hi>Hero,</hi> a <hi>Hercules,</hi> and all the fine Things a Man can think on; but turn it the other way, and then 'tis a <hi>Devil,</hi> a <hi>Nero,</hi> a <hi>Monſter:</hi> And to make it yet more piquant, put <hi>Dutch</hi> to all theſe, 'tis a <hi>Dutch Devil,</hi> a <hi>Dutch Nero,</hi> a <hi>Dutch Monſter;</hi> and if there be any thing worſe, 'tis even that too. And as <hi>Swearing, Allegiance,</hi> the Name <hi>King,</hi> mean one Thing in a State of Uſurpation, and the clean contrary under a Lawful Government; ſo, I ſuppoſe, for the ſame <hi>prudent Reaſon, does Glorious, Happy, Valiant, Deliverance.</hi> Theſe, and ſuch like, you are not to underſtand in their proper Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but in the Dreſs and Language of the Times: They are only Expreſſions <hi>de Facto,</hi> and if you think they mean any more by them you are much deceived; For why, I wonder, ſhould not they <hi>Speak</hi> as they <hi>Swear,</hi> and their <hi>Words</hi> as well as their <hi>Oaths</hi> have a temporary Meaning? However, Sir, you know that antiently <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Doemons</hi> were Synonimous, and Terms convertible: And why may not theſe Gentlemen call them by which they pleaſe, as they find occaſion, and according to the Seaſon?</p>
            <p>In the mean time let us, if you pleaſe, a little conſider the fine Knack theſe Gentlemen have got at Repreſentation and Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; which you will find ſo luſcious and termagant, as would ſhame even the Modeſty of the Stage. But here I muſt caution you not to extend what is ſaid to all, nor to apply it to any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom it does not belong: For I muſt tell you there is a Diſtinction to be made (and all wiſe Men d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtinguiſh them) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the old Church of <hi>England Men,</hi> who have taken the Oaths and Comply, and think they can acquit themſelves by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aint and Force that is put upon them; but ſtill retain their old Principles relating to the Monarchy and the Church, who are far the Beſt, the Wiſeſt, the Honeſteſt, and the moſt Num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59293:9"/>
Compliers. Theſe, though they ſatisfy themſelves in a compulſive Submiſſion, yet are too generous and honeſt to Deify their Chains, and Glory in their Bondage. A Man who hath got a heavy Load on his Back muſt bear it as well as he can; but that is no Reaſon to celebrate the Burthen, and extol it to the Skies, and give im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Honour to that which cripples him. Theſe therefore you muſt pretermit, and they are particularly and expreſly Excepted as no way Concerned in what follows. But then for your St <hi>A—phs,</hi> your <hi>Til—ns, Ten—ns, B—ts;</hi> your <hi>Sh—ks, Pat—cks, W—ks, Fl—ds:</hi> Theſe are the fine Sparks that do all the Feats we are ſpeaking of; who firſt themſelves ſwallow the Morſels of <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> and then dreſs it up with all the gawdy and ridiculous Flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſhes that an Apoſtate Eloquence can put upon it. I ſhall not ranſack all their Sermons; if you have a mind to ſuch Stuff you may find them all on the Stalls, or among the Hawkers.</p>
            <p>But to give you a Taſte, there are Two ways which they all take in order to accompliſh their End: The one is, to blacken all they can whom they think are not in their ungodly Intereſt, or obſtruct it; the other is, to magnify and advance that Intereſt as much on the other hand; but both very ſhameleſs, and you ſhall have a Touch of both.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Their goodly Method of <hi>Diſparaging</hi> and <hi>Reproaching.</hi> And this perhaps you may think foreign to the preſent Matter, which concerns their <hi>Praiſing</hi> and <hi>Commending</hi> Faculty: But however this (though it ſeems the contrary Extream) is in Truth not ſo wide of the Mark; but like Lines drawn from the contrary Sides of a Circle, centers in the very ſame Point. For beſides that, theſe were deſigned for <hi>Shadows,</hi> to ſet off the Picture they are ſhewing. There are ſome Men in the World who have not one fair Quality to be commended, and a Man cannot honeſtly ſay one good Word of them; and yet it is neceſſary for our purpoſe that they ſhould be commended, and that very highly too. And what is to be done in ſuch a Caſe? Why, when you cannot do it directly, you muſt go obliquely to your Matter; and that muſt be done by <hi>Compariſon,</hi> which hath no poſitive Excellency of it ſelf to admit of it. As for Inſtance, If I was to commend a <hi>Hawk,</hi> and in particular for its Mildneſs, Mercifulneſs, Compaſſion; That it is a Sweet-natur'd Bird, and a great Benefactor. Now to ſay this directly, and without any more ado, would look a little Scurvily, and Men would not eaſily ſwallow ſuch a Character of a Bird of Prey: But then you muſt go to work artificially, and tell them, There is a terrible and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59293:9"/>
rapacious <hi>Eagle,</hi> that hath Talons as long as one's Arm, and will ſwoop up a whole Flock at once; and then your <hi>Hawk</hi> may look like a pretty and lovely Fowl, and the Liberty and Property of the Birds are in a hopeful Condition, though he eats Three or Four of them at a Breakfaſt, and pulls all the Feathers from the Backs of the reſt. Now, Sir, according to this Method, if you have a Mind to ſee the Character of a Great <hi>Prince,</hi> thus it is in plain <hi>Engliſh:</hi>
               <note n="(a)">Dr. Sherlock be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Queen, June <hi>17. 1691.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Great Oppreſſor, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Tyranny and Powers;</hi> and <hi>one who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades and uſurps upon the Liberties of</hi> Europe. This is in ſhort, but if you will have it enlarg'd take it as follows;<note n="(b)">Dr. Tillotſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King and Queen, Oct. <hi>6. 1692.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Pride of all his Glory hath been ſtain'd by Tyranny and Oppreſſion, by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and Cruelty, by enlarging his Dominions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Right,</hi> (I pray mark that) <hi>and by making War upon his Neighbours without Reaſon, or even Colour or Provocation. And this in a more barbarous Manner than the moſt barbarous Nations ever did, carrying Fire and Deſolation whereſoever he went, and laying waſte many and great Cities, without Neceſſity, and without Pity.</hi> This is pretty well; but you may have it again in other Words thus. That<note n="(c)">Dr. Patrick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King and Queen, Ap. <hi>16. 1690.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Grand Oppreſſor,</hi> — who hath <hi>endeavoured to exalt his Nation by nothing but Fraud and Forgery, Perfidiouſneſs and Perjury, by breaking his Faith, and violating Leagues and Solemn Treaties, by Wrong and Robbery; nay, by the utmoſt degree of Cruelty and Barbarity: This haughty Oppreſſor, I ſay who hath ruin'd many other Countries as well as his own, hath highly affronted the Divine Majeſty, as well as abuſed all Mankind with whom they had to do.</hi> Who <hi>have been ſo Atheiſtical, as to advance themſelves by all manner of Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Treachery— Injuſtice and Cruelty, having mock'd at thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, Truth and Honeſty,</hi> &amp;c. Once more, and then I have done:<note n="(d)">Mr. Fleetwood before the L. Mayor, Apr. <hi>11. 1692.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Who does not deſcend to treat Embaſſadors villanouſly, but their Maſters; deals with them all as Vaſſals, or as Children; does not cut off their Garments to the middle but diveſts them of the Whole with mighty Scorn and Inſolence; and cuts not off their Beards, but pares them to the Quick. Is not at War with all his Neighbours only, but with Faith and Honour, Truth and Juſtice, and Religion; who knows no diſtinction betwixt Right and Wrong— One in a Word, That hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the ill Qualities of all the Ancient and Renown'd Sons of Violence, without the Shadow of their Vertues, or Pretence to any of their Merits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59293:10"/>Theſe, Sir, you muſt needs confeſs to be very high and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Flights, and cannot chuſe but operate and ſubdue our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and entirely Perſwade us: But here, I know you, will ask, <hi>And Perſwade us to what?</hi> Why, that we in <hi>England</hi> are infinitely Happy and Eaſy; That we know no Want, Poverty, or Calamity; That thoſe who have got the Government are the moſt Merciful, Juſt, and Righteous Perſons in the World: For thus you muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret their Words, or you miſtake the <hi>Preachers.</hi> Now this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may be very Rhetorical; but Rhetorick is a very dull Thing to perſwade a Man contrary to what he feels. Sure theſe Men think they have got an Aſcendant over our Senſes as well as our <hi>Conſciences:</hi> As if our real Oppreſſions and Miſeries were nothing at all, or were tranſmuted into <hi>Glories, Bounties,</hi> and <hi>Benefactions;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, forſooth, there are a People on this ſide the Line who are more oppreſſed and miſerable: Juſt as if you ſhould preach to a Man who hath his Fingers and Toes cut off, That he muſt not Complain, nor does he feel any Pain; becauſe there is a Man on the other ſide of the Water who cuts off Men's <hi>Legs,</hi> or <hi>Heads:</hi> Or juſt as if I ſhould tell you, That your Neighbour <hi>Lunt,</hi> and his Tutor <hi>A. S.</hi> are the honeſteſt People in the World; for that there is one <hi>T. O.</hi> who hath <hi>ſwore</hi> through an Inch Board, and <hi>Evidenc'd</hi> I know not how many to the Gallows, which the other only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, and by <hi>great Misfortune</hi> were not able to effect. Alas! Sir, real and poſitive Miſchiefs will not diminiſh into Nothing, nor change their Natures by all the Degrees of Compariſon; and Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs is Wickedneſs, let the Compariſon be what it will: And therefore ſuppoſe that all that theſe Men ſay were true, moſt of which is notwithſtanding falſe, What is that to us? We have Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries enough at home, without croſſing the Seas, and looking into other Countries. What do they tell us of the Furies and Scorpions of <hi>France,</hi> when we have in <hi>England</hi> too many Snakes and Vipers, that ſuck our Blood, and ſting us to Death? Let the <hi>French King</hi> be as great an <hi>Uſurper</hi> as theſe Men would have him, then that is the worſe for him; but never the better for us, who have <hi>Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> enough nearer hand to make all our Hearts ake. We know our own Oppreſſions, and feel them ſufficiently: And 'tis a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Buſineſs to plaiſter us o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er with an idle Tale out of the Pulpit, of Cannibals and Blood-ſuckers in the World of the Moon.</p>
            <p>But ſince theſe Gentlemen are for the Terms of Compariſon, if you pleaſe, we will follow them in their own way; and I am very much miſtaken if their own Methods does not turn upon them, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59293:10"/>
fly directly in their Faces; and thoſe amiable Characters they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for another Prince will, I doubt, much better become one nearer home.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Place, they tell us, <hi>This mighty Prince uſurps upon the Liberties of</hi> Europe: But methinks they might let <hi>Uſurpation</hi> alone; it is a very rank Word, and they all ſmell ſtrongly of it. For what hath this mighty Prince done to merit this Glorious Title? Why, if you conſult Fact, He hath been a little uncivil to the <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and hath taken ſome Towns from them: But then if it be <hi>Uſurpation</hi> to take a few Towns; What is it, I pray, to take Three whole Kingdoms? This, I ſuppoſe, may deſerve ſome Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminent Character: And if theſe Gentlemen will try their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, they have Epithets enough ready to dignify and diſtinguiſh it. The <hi>French King</hi> had no <hi>Father</hi> to uſurp upon, and therefore his Caſe is not altogether ſo meritorious: Beſides, he hath offered to reſtore the <hi>Towns</hi> upon honourable Conditions; which, as yet, I do not hear the <hi>Other</hi> is diſpoſed to do. So that, it ſeems, this great <hi>Leviathan,</hi> in this Point, hath not an <hi>Equal</hi> indeed; but it is becauſe there is one in the World <hi>much Greater;</hi> and as Great as he is, he muſt be forced to come behind him by many Degrees: And therefore I muſt needs ſubſcribe to Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> when he tells us, <hi>That a Greater than he is here.</hi> For whatſoever it may be with reſpect to other Vertues, it is moſt certain, That he far exceeds him in the Point of <hi>Uſurpation.</hi> It muſt be confeſſed indeed, That theſe Gentlemen have given a tolerable Account of <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> and have Stigmatized it too in their way; but then they have miſtaken the the Subject, by puzzling their Brains to find <hi>him</hi> in foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, when at the ſame they had <hi>him</hi> in their Eye; as if the Vices of Travellers had been tranſplanted to the Pulpit, to talk of every Trifle abroad, and neglect Things greater and more remarkable at our own Doors. Our own Country is fruitful enough; and ſurely in theſe days we need not go to <hi>France</hi> to look for an <hi>Uſurper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps it is not <hi>Uſurpation</hi> in general that theſe Men are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with; and it is plain they love it as their Eyes, and have ſtrein'd their Wits, their Pens, and their Conſciences, to procure and ſupport it: But <hi>Uſurpation</hi> limited to a particular Caſe, as they call it, <hi>Uſurping upon the Liberties of</hi> Europe. And this the ſame Reverend Doctor calls, <hi>The Liberties of Mankind,</hi> and all the reſt have it over and over: So that it ſeems let the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have <hi>Liberties</hi> enough, and then the Uſurping upon <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Thrones</hi> is a very innocent, nay a very juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59293:11"/>
Undertaking. By this Doctrine, if the <hi>French</hi> King had borrowed half the Provinces of <hi>Germany</hi> from the Empire, and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonia</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and at the ſame time had preſerved the Peoples legal Liberties, or given them greater; he might have been reconciled to theſe Gentlemens good Grace, and have been called a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and <hi>Deliverer</hi> too. Whereas I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thought, That ſo far as one Prince ſeized and deteined the Rights of another, he was ſo far an Uſurper, and ſo far guilty of Injuſtice; and whoſoever join'd with him in the Acquiring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported him in the Poſſeſſion, was involv'd in the Guilt, what uſe ſoever he made of his Power: But it ſeems if the People can make advantage of Uſurpation, and ſhare in the Spoil, 'tis very Holy and Glorious; and there is no Guilt ſticks to a fat Morſel, if theſe Gentlemen may but have their Parts of it. So that 'tis plain, by all their Harangues of <hi>Liberty,</hi> They mean their <hi>Liberty</hi> of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deans,</hi> the <hi>Liberty</hi> of fatning and warming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Shadow of <hi>Uſurpation:</hi> But if this be the <hi>Glorious Liberty</hi> they talk of, 'tis confin'd to themſelves; the collective Body of the People are perfect Strangers to it. All the Liberty this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion enjoys under this bleſſed Revolution, is a <hi>Liberty</hi> of giving Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Eight millions Year after Year, and a <hi>Liberty</hi> of loſing as much more; a <hi>Liberty</hi> of being firſt made Poor, and then Famiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Starved; a <hi>Liberty</hi> of having our Brethren and Country-men ſent into foreign Countries to be knockt on the Head; a <hi>Liberty</hi> of being Scorn'd by all Mankind, as the moſt Treacherous and Perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Nation in the World; and laſt of all, a <hi>Liberty</hi> of being Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed beyond Repair, and of being Ruin'd for ever. Theſe, and ſuch as theſe, are now our <hi>Glorious Liberties;</hi> and I defy the <hi>Perteſt</hi> of them all to ſhew me any other <hi>Liberty</hi> beſides, as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and immediate Fruits of the <hi>Revolution,</hi> which every one of theſe certainly is, and which no Man can have the Face to deny.</p>
            <p>Another goodly Character they beſtow on the <hi>Grand Oppreſſor</hi> (as they call him) is (as Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi> hath it) That <hi>he advanceth himſelf by breaketh his Faith, and violating Leagues and Solemn Treaties.</hi> Now this is certainly ſufficiently Evil in whomſoever it is: All the Doctor's Expreſſions of <hi>Perfidious, Fraud, Forgery, Robbery,</hi> and I know not how many more, do not ſufficiently intimate the Vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, only he hath a little miſtaken his Man, as he is very apt to do; but if he had pleas'd he might have found a much fitter Subject. For 'tis plain, That this ſaps the very Foundation of the Revolution, and in the firſt Conduct and Management of it.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59293:11"/>
There never was in the World, and no Hiſtory can parallel, ſuch a perfidious and notorious Violation of <hi>Faith, Leagues,</hi> and <hi>Solemn Treaties.</hi> For I pray, good Sir, was not King <hi>James</hi> at that time in perfect Peace and Amity with the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces?</hi> And this in purſuance of former <hi>Leagues</hi> and freſh <hi>Ratifications:</hi> So that if the Doctor pleaſe, he may take his <hi>Perfidious</hi> and <hi>Fraud</hi> again, and lay them on the right Horſe. But this is not all: The King had then an Embaſſador reſiding among them, and when he heard of their vaſt Preparations, he remonſtrated to them his Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion by his Embaſſador; and to give him Satisfaction, they gave him <hi>Solemn Aſſurance</hi> that they were not deſign'd againſt <hi>England.</hi> So that here we have both <hi>Solemn Leagues,</hi> and <hi>Solemn Aſſurances;</hi> and yet immediately after, and at the firſt Opportunity, (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſhew how they could keep theſe Sacred Bonds) they ſent over an Army to hunt him from his Throne and Kingdom. If therefore you are for the <hi>Violation of Leagues and Treaties,</hi> this is a Maſter-piece; here you have it in the fowleſt and moſt aggravating Circumſtances, and all the Records of Villany cannot ſhew us ſuch another. The <hi>Revolution</hi> is the Iſſue and Off-ſpring of it: It was bego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon <hi>breach of Faith,</hi> and in good Truth it fully reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles its <hi>Parent;</hi> and hath all the Features and Lineaments of the baſeſt Perfidiouſneſs and Treachery the World ever ſaw. The <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of it was breach of Leagues, and of the publick Faith of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and the <hi>Mother</hi> was Rebellion and Perjury; and from theſe is ſprung a bleſſed Reformation compounded of all Four.</p>
            <p>Another Character we have, and that is, That <hi>he makes War upon his Neighbours without Reaſon or Colour of Provocation.</hi> Now 'tis certain that the <hi>Reaſons</hi> ought to be very <hi>Juſt,</hi> and the <hi>Provocations</hi> very <hi>Great,</hi> before a War can be juſtified which will coſt ſo many Lives on both Sides: but for all that, I do not think every Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Theolog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is qualified to judge of <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Provocations,</hi> how wiſe ſoever he may think himſelf. Theſe often lie as deep as Myſteries of State, and the Councels of Princes, which are quite out of their Sphere; and they are no more able to underſtand them, than they can fathom the Councels and In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gues of all the Princes of <hi>Europe.</hi> So that whether the <hi>French</hi> King hath, or hath not, any Reaſons or Provocations, they are very flippant with their Tongues, but they know nothing of the Matter: And 'tis equal Weakneſs and Confidence to pronounce peremptorily of what they neither do, nor can underſtand. However, if he wanted <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Provocations,</hi> theſe Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lemen have taken extraordinary Care
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59293:12"/>
to ſupply that Defect by loading him with all the foul and naſty Language they can think on; and diſcharging on his Perſon all the rank Venom that is in their Breaſts. And ſince we are upon <hi>Provocations,</hi> methinks theſe Men ſhould give us a <hi>Reaſon</hi> why they have been <hi>provoked</hi> to ſuch unchriſtian, unmannerly, and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Expreſſions of a Great Prince, which a modeſt Man would never be provoked to ſay of a Porter, or the meaneſt Varlet on the Face of the Earth. Which plainly ſhews from whence they had their Divinity; and what fine Doctrin we are to expect from Sermons ſtufft with the boldeſt Reproaches of <hi>Crown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Heads</hi> that were ever heard among Chriſtian People. For, as I take it, that Precept <hi>not to ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> is not limited to a Country, or particular So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty, to thoſe only who have immediate and direct Authority over us; but extends to all lawful Sovereigns and Governors. And though we owe no Allegiance to a Foreign Prince, yet certainly we owe him Decency, Reſpect and Modeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let him be Friend or Enemy. The Station and Character he holds, and the Image he bears, and the Authority he is inveſted with (which Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> rolls us is always God's Authority) are Things too Sacred to be Lampoon'd and Burleſqu'd; to be treated with Infamy and Scorn by every petulant Tongue. But let theſe <hi>moderate</hi> Gentlemen uſe their Tongues as they pleaſe, and Rail as long as they will (and perhaps they may think they have a <hi>Latitude</hi> in that too) they have a very good Will at it, but are very unfortunate withal; for it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways comes home to them, and turns directly upon them, as in the preſent Inſtance; Whether the <hi>French</hi> King hath ſome <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Provocations,</hi> with reſpect to the reſt of his Neighbours, or none at all? 'Tis as plain as the Sun, That he hath both <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Provocations</hi> too, with reſpect of us: For if theſe Gentlemen will look again, they will find that he did not firſt make War upon us, but we made War upon him; and that, I ſuppoſe, will go for a <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Provocation.</hi> And 'tis extremely Ridiculous to talk of no <hi>Reaſons,</hi> or <hi>Colour</hi> of <hi>Provocation,</hi> for entering into a War, when we began it our ſelves: And if <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Provocations</hi> muſt be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, they ought to come from the <hi>firſt Aggreſſors.</hi> And it will certainly near concern the Conſciences of <hi>ſome,</hi> to have ſome good Reaſons ready for the entering in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſo expenſive and dangerous a War; or elſe all the Blood that hath been unneceſſarily ſpilt will lie at their Doors, and they will have a large Account to make for Ravaging and Depopulating three Rich and Flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, meerly to ſatisfy their inſatiable Pride and Ambition. I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59293:12"/>
know well enough that the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is talkt on, but that is meer Pretence, Sham, and Nonſenſe; a Stale to delude the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to cover ſomething elſe: For beſides that the greateſt part of the Confederates are rank Papiſts (and 'tis the utmoſt Folly to think they would enter into a Confederacy for the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>) The two Kings of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> are as good Proteſtants (and a little better than thoſe who ſo much pretend it;) yet had Wit enough to keep themſelves out of the Fire: And I defy the Wit of Man to aſſign any more than one Reaſon, and one Provocation, of this terrible War on our ſide, and neither of them <hi>Juſt, Honourable,</hi> or <hi>Neceſſary.</hi> The <hi>Reaſon</hi> plainly is the skeening our Neighbours the <hi>Dutch;</hi> and our Men and Money muſt be ſent thither for no other <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but to ſave their Pockets, and their Skins; and, I doubt, this will never paſs for an <hi>honourable Reaſon</hi> among <hi>Engliſhmen:</hi> That 'tis worth ſuch prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Quantities of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Treaſure and Blood to fight their Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and ſecure their Frontiers; or that <hi>Loo</hi> is ſuch a delicate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, that Three Kingdoms muſt be Beggar'd and Exhauſted to the very Bones, meerly to preſerve a Prince's <hi>Hunting, and his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to eat Bread and Cheeſe with a Farmer's Daughter.</hi> Thus much for the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of this conſuming War; and I will leave any <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who hath not loſt his Reaſon as well as his Conſcience, to judge of it. The next is the <hi>Provocation;</hi> and this, I know, will a little puzzle you to find it out: But I can eaſily ſatisfy you, It was that King's entertaining King <hi>James.</hi> This, it ſeems, was ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly <hi>Provoking,</hi> and <hi>Exaſperating,</hi> that our <hi>Heroe</hi> could not bear it; but he muſt be perſued with Deſolation and Vengeance, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can expiate but his Crown: For you may remember, that at the beginning of the War, nothing leſs would ſatisfy us, but ſetting up our Standard at <hi>Paris,</hi> and humbling the <hi>Monſieur.</hi> As if becauſe they had driven him from his Kingdoms, he muſt, for that Reaſon, be made a Vagabond in the Earth; and thoſe who had <hi>Abdicated</hi> him from his Throne, would (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they might have had their Will) have <hi>Abdicated</hi> him from all the World too: And becauſe they had hunted him from his own Home, he muſt have no retiring Place, nor where to lay his Head; which is neither more nor leſs, than that we did not think it convenient to Kill him our ſelves, but ſhould be glad with all our Hearts to have him Starved Abroad. For 'tis an infallible Maxim, That he who <hi>Uſurps</hi> another Prince's Throne, can never be at reſt ſo long as the <hi>Right Owner</hi> is Living. And now, Sir, you have this goodly <hi>Provocation,</hi> which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59293:13"/>
plainly founded in the Injuries we our ſelves have done; and the whole Nation muſt be ſacrificed to Revenge that generous Pity and Compaſſion which hath been ſhewn to an <hi>Oppreſſed Prince,</hi> and whom we have infinitely wronged. Whatſoever therefore the <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers</hi> talk of Oppreſſion, Fraud, Robbery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'tis none of <hi>theſe</hi> that offend us: 'Tis not his Oppreſſion, but his <hi>Piety,</hi> is the Ground of this immortal Hatred; and 'tis manifeſt to all, That the Noble, Princely, and Chriſtian Succour he hath afforded our injur'd King, is more <hi>provoking</hi> than all the <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>To this may be added what immediately follows in the ſame Sermon. <hi>And this</hi> (making War) <hi>in a more barbarous Manner than the moſt barbarous Nations ever did, carrying Fire and Deſolation, and laying waſte many and great Cities, without Neceſſity, and without Pity.</hi> Theſe indeed are the terrible Effects of War, but then they are as common as they are terrible: For whatever our Author may talk of <hi>a more barbarous Manner than the barbarous Nations ever did;</hi> there never was any War in the World where there wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not more or leſs of this. And there is nothing more common than for angry Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to raze Towns, and plunder the Inhabitants. And had our Author underſtood any Hiſtory, or knew how to ſpeak Truth, he might have read, That nothing was more Cruel than the Wars of <hi>barbarous Nations;</hi> and without going any further, he might have found in his <hi>Bible,</hi> had he thought it for his Purpoſe, That <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar</hi> not only burnt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but carried away the whole Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> Captive: And it was uſual in thoſe days for Conquerors to drive a whole Country, and replant it with their own Native Subjects; and the Conqueſt of <hi>Samaria</hi> is another dreadful Inſtance of it. Which (as I take it) is a far greater <hi>Waſte</hi> and <hi>Deſolation</hi> than firing a few Towns, and deſtroying a Crop of Corn, or ſome Vineyards. But perhaps our Author had not his <hi>Bible</hi> ready, but might think it more ſuitable to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter to inform himſelf from <hi>News-Books,</hi> and <hi>Welwood</hi>'s <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator;</hi> although another Man in a leſs Poſt than an <hi>Archbiſhoprick</hi> might have thought <hi>that Book</hi> as fit to be conſulted with in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Sermons,</hi> as the <hi>London Gazette,</hi> or the <hi>Haerlem Courant.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this plainly ſhews theſe Gentlemen's admirable Faculty at <hi>Compariſon:</hi> They cannot forbear it, although at the ſame time they ſpeak not one Word of Truth. But <hi>Compariſons</hi> (whether true or falſe) make a great Noiſe, and are <hi>Fine Strokes,</hi> (as <hi>Dyer</hi> ſays;) and Divines have ſomething elſe to do, nor does it become the Place to deliver <hi>plain Truth</hi> in their <hi>Court Sermons.</hi> In the mean
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59293:13"/>
time 'twould be well if all Wars could be managed without <hi>Waſte</hi> and <hi>Deſolation,</hi> but that never was, nor ever will be; and perhaps it is impoſſible it ſhould be: And whatever the Caſes are that may ſeem to require it, I do not think that any <hi>Preacher</hi> of them all ſo fit a Judge of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Pity,</hi> as the Generals of Armies, who know much better than they what it is that an Enemy can make Advantage of. And, for my own part, I believe their lodges in the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſt of a Great and Valiant General, a Thouſand times more <hi>Generoſity</hi> and <hi>Pity,</hi> than in a <hi>Smooth-tongu'd Divine,</hi> who can preach up <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deration</hi> when it is a popular Theme; and yet turn out a moſt Reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end Prelate (much better than himſelf) from his Legal and Rightful Poſſeſſion, in a moſt violent and <hi>barbarous</hi> Manner. But let that be as it will, the <hi>Compariſon</hi> turns home upon them: Let the <hi>French</hi> King have carried as much <hi>Fire</hi> as they pleaſe; let him have laid Waſte as <hi>many and great Cities</hi> as they think good; the <hi>Confederates</hi> have not been behind hand with him in <hi>good Will,</hi> and have executed it too as far as they had Power; and if they have not altogether ſo fully performed it, it is not owing to their <hi>Pity,</hi> but to the Conduct and Power of their Adverſary. If a Man has a great Mind to cut my Throat, and very heartily Attempts it, but through my own Care, Vigilance, or Courage, he is not able to do it; I ſuppoſe I am not beholding to his Vertue, but to his Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency. However, it is not very long ſince we have given ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inſtance of our great <hi>Pity</hi> in this kind; and the laſt <hi>Summers Expedition</hi> will abundantly exemplify our mighty Vertue in forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to burn Towns <hi>without Neceſſity or Pity,</hi> when we attempted upon <hi>La Hogue</hi> and <hi>Breſt:</hi> And becauſe we could do nothing there, for very Anger we bombarded <hi>Diep,</hi> and bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt it to the Ground; a defenceleſs Maritim Town, and which was neither a Harbour for Men of War, nor Gariſon for Soldiers, nor held any Magazine for Proviſions and Ammunition, and (which is more than all this) was the only Seat left for the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and where they were very Numerous. And you cannot but remember what care was taken to publiſh and magnify the Bravery of this great Exploit, of conſuming a weak Town, and firing the poor <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> out of their Houſes: Whereas had it been never ſo uſeful, the Expedition coſt us Five times the Value of it; and it is great Matter of Triumph indeed, to boaſt of the Damage of a Penny we have done to an Enemy, though, by the doing of it, we our ſelves ſuſtain the Loſs of Five Shillings. However, from theſe Premiſſes this Concluſion follows; That if the firing of Towns <hi>without Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59293:14"/>
and without Pity,</hi> be more Barbarous than Barbarity it ſelf, we muſt take this Honour to our ſelves, for it plainly lies at our own Doors.</p>
            <p>But ſince we are upon <hi>Barbarity,</hi> I will give you ſuch an Inſtance of it as no Age, Hiſtory, nor Nation (Barbarous or not Barbarous) can parallel. What do you think of <hi>hanging</hi> Priſoners taken in War in cold Blood, upon the Pretence and by the Formality of Law? You may try your Reading, and ſee if the moſt <hi>Barbarous Nations,</hi> or the moſt <hi>Barbarous Men,</hi> did ever do the like. And yet I need not tell of Three who were actually <hi>hang'd,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral are now in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and under Condemnation: I ſhall not trouble you with the whole Caſe; all the Nation knows it, and all good Men abhor it. It is ſufficient to obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve, That not one, nor all together of the various <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> thoſe Gentlemen go upon, that will excuſe it from down right <hi>Murther:</hi> Let it be <hi>Abdication,</hi> or <hi>King de Facto,</hi> or <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> or <hi>Providence,</hi> or whatever their winding Inventions, and changeable Conſciences, can think on; it is up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all <hi>Murther,</hi> and the moſt <hi>Barbarous Murther</hi> under the Sun. For the ſingle Queſtion is no more but this, Whether a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject following the Fortune of his Prince, and never acknowledging the Authority of any other, I ſay, Whether ſuch a Perſon ſighting under the Commiſſion of his own Prince, or his Allie, be an <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> or a <hi>Pirate</hi> and <hi>Traytor?</hi> Let theſe Men, and all their Party together, try their Skill, and conſider but their own <hi>Hypotheſes,</hi> and excuſe or palliate it if they can: But it does and will remain upon Record, the moſt hideous Cruelty, and the greateſt Violation of the common Rights of Mankind, that ever was heard of. I Scorn ſo much as to take Notice of that Pamphlet wrought in Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it: It diſcovers ſo much of the <hi>Fool</hi> and the <hi>Knave,</hi> that it is impoſſible any Man ſhould be impoſed upon, who has not as high a Degree of theſe Qualities as the Author himſelf. In the mean time, the true Reaſon of this makes it Ten times worſe; and that is, they were not Comprehended in the <hi>Cartel</hi> between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Confederates</hi> As if in the Caſe of <hi>Blood,</hi> and the Lives of Men, Princes were not to be determined by the common Rules of Equity; the Laws of War, and of Nations; and the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Conſent of Mankind; but by particular <hi>Cartel.</hi> At this Rate, if there was no <hi>Cartel</hi> nor Agreement between Enemies (which is very rare) you might juſtly and honorably hang up in cold Blood as many Priſoners as you could take, which is <hi>Waſte</hi> and <hi>Deſolation</hi> with a vengeance. One would think that the Laws of God and Nature,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59293:14"/>
and the common Principles of Humanity, might be ſufficient to reſtrain Men, as well as particular Covenants, which are Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent and Superiour to all ſuch Covenants, and can never be cancell'd by them; and in truth are more Sacred and Inviolable than all the <hi>Cartels</hi> in the World. The great <hi>Leviathan</hi> himſelf (as they call him) might have taught them more Temperament and Humanity; who at ſeveral times, and particularly in the laſt Battel in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> took Duke <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and many others of his own <hi>Native Subjects,</hi> Priſoners; and yet very honourably Releaſed the <hi>Duke,</hi> and not one of the reſt were Condemned either to the Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet or the Gallies. And yet the Caſe was very different, and all the Advantages were on the Side of theſe poor Men, excepting only the Qualities of the Judges. But I am perfectly weary of this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Subject, and which no Man can think of without the greateſt Horrour.</p>
            <p>The laſt good Quality theſe Gentlemen take notice of is this; That <hi>he does not treat Embaſſadors villainouſly, but their Maſters; does not cut off their Garments to the middle, but diveſts them of the Whole; and cuts not off their Beards, but pares them to the Quick.</hi> By this, Sir, you are to underſtand that the <hi>French</hi> King is a <hi>clean Shaver;</hi> that when he takes <hi>Princes</hi> in hand, he leaves them neither <hi>Hair,</hi> nor <hi>Nails,</hi> nor <hi>Fleſh</hi> on their Backs; nay, 'tis much if he has not a Slice of their very <hi>Bones.</hi> But the plain Engliſh of this frothy and boyiſh Ribaldry is this, That he diveſts them of their Dominions, takes away from them all that they have, and ſends them into fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Countries to beg their Bread, and live upon the Charity of well diſpoſed People. Now, Sir, I deſire you by all means to ſhut your Eyes, and not to look about you; for if you do, upon ſuch a Character, you will be terribly tempted to think upon Somebody or other within the <hi>four Seas.</hi> For, as I remember, King <hi>James</hi> ſat upon the Throne of his Anceſtors, was himſelf a wealthy Prince, and govern'd Three rich and flouriſhing Kingdoms: I remember likewiſe, that this very Prince was diveſted of his Crown, and of all that he had beſides in the World; and he, his Queen, and Princely Babe, were forced to fly into a Foreign Land for Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, Shelter and Security. Now if Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> will pleaſe to tell us who did all this, there he will certainly find his Man, <hi>that does not deſcend to treat Embaſſadors villanouſly, but their Maſters; that diveſts them of the While, and pares them to the Quick</hi> And to to compleat his Character he may add, if he pleaſe, <hi>That pares the People as well as the Prince to the Quick.</hi> For theſe Three unhappy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59293:15"/>
Nations were never <hi>par'd ſo near</hi> as they have been by a <hi>Dutch Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Knife,</hi> ſince the beginning of the World.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I have given you a Taſte of theſe Gentlemens <hi>Invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Faculty, and you ſee how fairly they have handled it to the Honour of their Maſter; they name another Perſon indeed, but it is not whom they name, but whom they deſcribe, and the World will apply it. Satyr is a very keen Thing indeed, but then it hath two Edges, and cuts both ways; and when they give ſuch broad <hi>Innuendoes,</hi> People will be tempted to think, that it is meerly Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical, They perſonate one Man, and mean another: And I doubt they will be ſuſpected of <hi>deep and dangerous Deſigns againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> for thus terribly reflecting on the <hi>Valiant Heroe</hi> through the Sides of the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, Their Sermons are nothing elſe but ſo many Scandalous Reflexions upon <hi>him,</hi> on another Account. And they have but little conſulted his Honour, or Fame, when they can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Face, in that groſs Manner, traduce and beſpatter his Enemy, and with whom he is actually at War: A brave and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Adverſary will fight his Enemy fairly and valiantly, but ſcorns and abhors theſe mean and ſordid Acts of Reviling and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; and whatever they talk, they certainly have a very mean Opinion of him, when they think they can divert and gratify him with perpetual Reproaches and Aſperſions; or that he can have Patience to hear every day from the Pulpit ſuch a Peal of dirty Language. Suppoſe now a conceited <hi>French Fryar,</hi> who had a mind to get Preferment, ſhould get up at the <hi>Louvre,</hi> and harangue to that King in this Manner.</p>
            <p>
               <q>There is a Prince in the World who hath endeavour'd to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance himſelf by Fraud and Forgery, by Perfidiouſneſs and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, and all the worſt Arts in the World; who, at his firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out, and aſſuming an high Poſt of Dignity in his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, it was by Two of the moſt hideous Crimes that Mankind knows. Firſt, by <hi>Perjury,</hi> having himſelf directly, and in ſo many Words, <hi>Swore</hi> that he would not take it; and then by <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> in a moſt barbarous and cruel Manner, cutting off Two of the beſt Patriots of his Country for oppoſing it. One, who with the greateſt Eaſe breaks through all the Bonds of Nature, Humanity and Relation, to gain his Ends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And while he was Courting the <hi>Daughter,</hi> at the ſame time was Undermining the <hi>Father,</hi> and laying Trains to ruin and deprive him of his <hi>Birth-right.</hi> One, who hath ever been harbouring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59293:15"/>
and cheriſhing <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Malecontents,</hi> to ſet a peaceable King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in a Flame, on purpoſe that he might come and make a Prey of it for himſelf. One, who hath ſo little Senſe of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, or Solemn Treaties, or Tenderneſs for the Blood of Men, That when he thought he had the Advantage, he actually fought an Army with the <hi>Articles of Peace</hi> in his Pocket. One of that prodigious and greedy Ambition, That he tramples upon all that is Sacred, upon Right, Juſtice, and the very Neck of his Father, to obtain a Throne. One, whoſe Gratitude is equal to his Juſtice, and proves falſe even to his Makers and Benefactors; and when he hath done his Buſineſs by their Aſſiſtance, he treads them under Foot, and diſcards them. There was a Time when a <hi>Pair of Jack Boots</hi> had very well deſerved of him, whom he now deſpiſes and ſcorns; and hath raiſed a couple of Mongrels over his Head. One, in fine, who is ſo much delighted with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, Scandals, and Defamations upon Great Princes, That he bribes and hires a Company of <hi>Foul-mouth'd</hi> Theologues of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Conſciences to recreate him once a Week, with all the nauſeous Scum and Filth they are able to rake together; and then puts his own Stamp upon it, and publiſhes it to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by <hi>SPECIAL COMMAND,</hi> which is the ſame Thing as if he had ſaid it himſelf: For though the Sermon or Words are not his, the Publication is; and he becomes a Party to all the opprobrious Expreſſions, by whoſe particular and immediate Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they are Printed and made Publick. That is, Theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen ſay all theſe vile Things to him, and he ſpeaks them to all the Kingdom.</q>
Now, Sir, what Reſentment do you think this Preachment would meet at the hands of the <hi>French</hi> King? I ſhall not undertake to anſwer that Queſtion; but this I can tell you, That if he have no more Generoſity nor Princely Vertues than other People, the Preacher would certainly be made a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or at leaſt a <hi>Dean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the Character they give of a <hi>Great Prince;</hi> but there are other People, of an inferior Rank, that they have an aking Tooth at; ſome call them <hi>Jacobites,</hi> and others <hi>Non Jurors.</hi> But here they are as hard put to it as ever Men were; they would be glad with all their Hearts that the People ſhould have an ill Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them, but then they do not know how to bring it to paſs. They have the ſame good Will, but there is ſome difference in the Subject. The <hi>French</hi> King is a great way off, and they think the People will rather believe them, than trouble themſelves to take
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59293:16"/>
a long Journey to diſprove them: But theſe Men live among us, and their Principles and Practices are well known, and therefore they cannot be ſo copious on this Subject: However you ſhall hear what they do ſay, and beſides ſome few canting Expreſſions, as <hi>Some amongſt us,</hi> and <hi>Kind Friends to the Liberties of</hi> Europe (as Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> hath it) which perhaps may paſs for Jibes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Jeſts; but ſure they do not expect that the very loweſt of the People ſhould take them for A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>guments, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Proofs. All the reſt is comprehended in what follows.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, The <hi>paucity of their Numbers.</hi> This is the common Topick, and runs through them all; and yet there is not one of them but knows full well, that this means nothing at all. That <hi>Truth</hi> was never tryed by Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, and telling of Noſes; that <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> were never any Evidence of a Good Cauſe: As if the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of Religion, and Points of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſcience, were to be meaſur'd like Armies, by the Strength of their Numbers. At this rate the <hi>Alcoran</hi> will vye with the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Turciſm</hi> will be not only better than <hi>Popery</hi> (as Father <hi>T.</hi> hath it) but even than <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf. This therefore is nothing elſe but Cheating and Deluding the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, inſtead of Informing and Inſtructing them. And they are hard put to it ſure, when to ſave their own Credit, and to blaſt others, they are forced ſo frequently to inculcate ſuch an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they themſelves in their own Conſciences, (if they have any) know to be none at all.</p>
            <p>The next is, That as they are few, ſo thoſe few are blind, and cannot ſee <hi>Providence</hi> (as Dr. <hi>Til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> hath it)<note n="*">Sermon before the King and Queen, Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tob. <hi>27. 1692.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>God has of late viſibly made bare his Arm in our behalf, though ſome are ſtill ſo blind and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate that they will not ſee it.</hi> And here we have got another <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Argument: Since theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen can find no Reaſons for their purpoſe in the <hi>Bible;</hi> but however if <hi>Mahomet</hi> has any, they will never want. For if <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> be an Argument, the <hi>Great Turk</hi> will be better able to plead it from the Foundation of that Religion, than any, or all the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the World: For I am very ſure <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> never got Footing in any Kingdom by <hi>Diſpoſſeſſing</hi> or <hi>Rebelling</hi> againſt the Lawful Governors, let them be of what Religion they would; but by the contrary Methods of <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Suffering.</hi> And therefore we honeſtly confeſs, That we cannot <hi>See</hi> that the <hi>long Sword</hi> is a <hi>Chriſtian Argument,</hi> nor fit to be made uſe of by any but <hi>Infidels.</hi> Our Author himſelf but eight Lines before ſays, That <hi>meer Succeſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59293:16"/>
is certainly one of the worſt Arguments in the World of a Good Cauſe:</hi> So it ſeems we are ſo <hi>very Blind</hi> that we <hi>cannot See</hi> the <hi>worſt Argument</hi> in the World to be the <hi>very beſt.</hi> And if that be our Fault, I doubt we ſhall never mend it, till we get not only their <hi>Spectacles,</hi> but their <hi>Conſciences</hi> too. But if <hi>Succeſſes be an Argument ſo very bad,</hi> What is it that theſe Gentlemen would have us to <hi>See?</hi> We are not ſo <hi>very Blind</hi> but we <hi>See</hi> the <hi>Succeſſes</hi> they talk on: We <hi>See Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the place of <hi>Right,</hi> and we <hi>See</hi> God's Hand in this too; in ſending Afflictions and Puniſhments upon a Proteſtant People for their <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Apoſtacy:</hi> We <hi>See</hi> further that they have a very <hi>bad Argument</hi> to manage; and they affront the Divine Providence, as well as abuſe the People, by perpetually infuſing into the illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Multitude ſuch Arguments which themſelves acknowledg to be the worſt in the World. Our Author indeed tells us, (<hi>ib. p</hi> 32.) <hi>That the Cauſe muſt firſt be manifeſtly Juſt, before Succeſs can be an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of God's Favour to it, and Approbation of it.</hi> Now 'tis certain that every Cauſe that is <hi>manifeſtly Juſt</hi> hath <hi>God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Favour and Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation;</hi> whether that Cauſe hath <hi>external Succeſs</hi> or no, or whether the Perſons engaged in it be proſpered by Divine Providence; which makes it as clear as the Light, that the Diſtinction is to be made not from Providence, and outward Succeſſes, but from the Juſtice of the Cauſe: And the <hi>Oppreſſed,</hi> notwithſtanding all the Harangues theſe Men make of <hi>viſible Providences,</hi> may be far more Righteous than their <hi>Oppreſſors.</hi> And I am very certain that this Man, who thus accuſes us of <hi>Blindneſs</hi> for not ſeeing of Providences, hath not ſaid one ſingle Word to convince us, or any rational Man, of the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of his Cauſe, and much leſs of the <hi>manifeſt</hi> Juſtice of it. And all that he does ſay, you have in thoſe two Hypothetical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions as it immediately follows; — <hi>If the Cauſe of true Religion, and the neceſſary Defence of it againſt a falſe and idolatrous Worſhip, be a good Cauſe, ours is ſo.</hi> Again, — <hi>If the Vindication of the common Liberties of Mankind againſt Tyranny and Oppreſſion be a goood Cauſe, ours is ſo.</hi> This is what our Author offers to make his Cauſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>manifeſtly</hi> Juſt; and in truth <hi>all</hi> that he offers on that Head: And yet both his Propoſitions are notoriouſly and ſcandalouſly Falſe. For you muſt know, that by the <hi>neceſſary Defence of Religion,</hi> he does not mean a <hi>Defence</hi> by the Words of <hi>Truth and Soberneſs,</hi> by Meekneſs, Patience and Suffering, which were the Defences of the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Chriſtians; but a Defence of Swords and Guns; a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by Arms, which is pure and perfect <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and the Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in of the <hi>Mufti,</hi> and roots up the Foundation of Chriſtianity. For
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59293:17"/>
if <hi>Religion</hi> may be defended by <hi>Arms,</hi> it may alſo be propagated by them; and for Men to talk of defending their Religion, and ſecuring their Conſciences by Arms, is a fit Doctrin only for ſuch <hi>Hypocritical Conſciences,</hi> who can hold their Principles no longer than they are backt with Secular Power. And this is yet Ten times worſe when 'tis applied to juſtify Uſurpation, and the Rebellion of Subjects under a Prince of another Religion; which is plainly the Caſe our Author drives at: For then he might know, That it is not only a <hi>Good Cauſe,</hi> but ſufficient <hi>Authority;</hi> 'tis not only a <hi>Good End,</hi> but <hi>Lawful Means</hi> alſo, that will warrant the entering into Arms; all theſe muſt concur to juſtify a War, and yet there is neither of theſe in this Caſe. For though true Religion be the beſt Cauſe in the World, yet it never was, nor ever will be, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Cauſe to take Arms upon; and God never gave Authority to a Foreigner, eſpecially one who is not a Sovereign Prince, to call another Prince to Account for his Religion, much leſs to make War on him on that Account; and God, nor our Laws, ever gave Subjects the Power ef the Sword to defend themſelves, and much leſs their Religion, by Arms and downright Rebellion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Concluſion is the direct contrary to that of our Author; That if the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> the <hi>Authority,</hi> the <hi>Means,</hi> be all and every one of them <hi>Unjuſt,</hi> then their <hi>Cauſe</hi> is ſo, and the Caſe is the very ſame with reſpect to the other <hi>Propoſition:</hi> But to make ſhort work of it, The Impiety and Falſhood of both theſe Propoſitions is plainly and irrefragably demonſtrated from theſe following Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions. Was not the Religion of our Saviour, and his Apoſtles, the <hi>true Religion?</hi> And were not their Supreme Governors at that time <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and the Religion of <hi>Heathen Rome, Idolatry?</hi> In like manner was not the whole Nation of <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, at that time under great <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> (as <hi>Tyranny</hi> means the Exerciſe of illegal and arbitrary Power?) Let theſe Queſtions be but fairly and honeſtly anſwered, and it will put an end to all Rebellious Hypotheſes; and in particular directly anſwer all and every one of the Aſſertions and Arguments of theſe Gentlemen. And for the Two firſt Queſtions they anſwer themſelves; and for the Third, let Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> anſwer, who in plain terms (in his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Letter,</hi> p. 9. 11, 12.) aſſerts, That the very <hi>ſhew of Freedom</hi> that was left the <hi>Jews</hi> was extinct after the Death of <hi>Herod; That</hi> Julius Ceſar <hi>and</hi> Auguſtus <hi>became the Uſurpers of the Liberties of their Country; That the Deſign</hi> Tiberius <hi>purſued was to overthrow all that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t of their Freedom, and to rob the People of ſuch of their Liberties as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59293:17"/>
yet remained, which was yet more barefac'd and black under</hi> Caligula. This is the direct Caſe of both the Doctor's Propoſitions, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in as ſevere Circumſtances as the World ever ſaw. Here was <hi>true Religion</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and under the Power of it: Here was <hi>Liberty</hi> Oppoſed to, and under the Oppreſſion of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</hi> And I hope theſe Gentlemen will grant that our Saviour, and his Apoſtles, had as much Care of <hi>Religion,</hi> as much Zeal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and were as Tender of the <hi>Liberties of Mankind,</hi> as any of them all. And yet they determine the Caſe in plain Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Contradiction to theſe Men: For inſtead of <hi>True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> fighting againſt <hi>Falſe and Idolatrous Worſhip;</hi> inſtead of vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating <hi>Liberty</hi> againſt <hi>Tyranny,</hi> we have the clean contrary; and both <hi>Doctrine, Precept, Example,</hi> teaching us to obey, ſubmit to, not to reſiſt, <hi>Idolatrous and Tyrannical Powers.</hi> And 'tis very remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, That 'tis in his <hi>Epiſtle to the Romans,</hi> that is, to thoſe very People, and in theſe very Circumſtances, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> does ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and particularly injoyn theſe Duties. This Gentleman is very pleaſant with us, and rallies us for being <hi>Blind,</hi> and cannot ſee bare fac'd Providences: And to give him a Caſt of his Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, We are indeed ſo <hi>Blind</hi> that we do not <hi>See</hi> any Reaſon to prefer the Aſſertions and Determinations of any <hi>Uſurping</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate</hi> Biſhop, before thoſe of our Saviour and his Apoſtles; but then we are not ſo <hi>Blind</hi> but we can <hi>See</hi> what all the World both <hi>Sees</hi> and talks on: We <hi>See,</hi> as well as other People, their <hi>Shame,</hi> their <hi>Infamy,</hi> their <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and <hi>intolerable Confidence,</hi> not only to obtrude theſe ſcandalous Doctrines upon us, but to contradict in expreſs Terms their own Doctrines and Aſſertions. For this very Man hath delivered a Doctrine as directly contrary to this as Words can expreſs; and that upon a very ſolemn and ſerious Occaſion, when he was to direct and ſettle the Conſcience of a <hi>Dying Lord.</hi> And he had in his Life-time been often and earneſtly called upon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile it to his preſent Opinion, and Practices; but he could never be prevailed upon to undertake it. And this is the Caſe of them all; they have <hi>Confidence</hi> enough to talk over and repeat their new Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, but will neither anſwer our Arguments, nor their own. And neither the Clamour of the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> nor their own Conſciences, nor the Satisfaction of the People, nor to clear their own Reputation from ſo foul a Scandal, could ever yet perſwade Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi> to anſwer his <hi>Paraphraſes,</hi> Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> his <hi>Preface to the Jeſuits Loyalty,</hi> Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> his <hi>Dialogues,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> his <hi>Caſe of Reſiſtance,</hi> his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> &amp;c. They have indeed advanc'd themſelves to Poſts of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59293:18"/>
by clean contrary Doctrines, which they <hi>Preach,</hi> and <hi>Preach</hi> over and over; but the other old Doctrines ſtand ſtill Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancelled, and have not been Delivered away by any direct Act and Deed. They own and preach up other Doctrines, but they will neither formally renounce theſe, nor yet reconcile them to their new Opinions and Practices: And there is good Reaſon for both; to <hi>reconcile</hi> them is <hi>impoſſible,</hi> and to <hi>renounce</hi> them <hi>inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</hi> For there may a Time come when ſuch Doctrines may be in Faſhion again, even as heretofore.</p>
            <p>The laſt Thing that is taken Notice of concerning theſe <hi>Non-Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> is their <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> their <hi>horrible Ingratitude:</hi> For thus Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> acquaints his Auditory,<note n="*">Serm. before the Queen, Sep. <hi>16. 1691.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>To whom by too many among us, the moſt unworthy and unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Returns have been made—that ever was made to ſo great and generous a Benefactor.</hi> Now the Doctor does not tell us who he means by this ſame <hi>too many among us;</hi> but ſure he cannot mean thoſe who have given him ſo many <hi>Millions:</hi> For one would think they have been ſufficiently Thankful, except the Doctor thought they could not expreſs their Gratitude, unleſs they had given him their Bodies and their Souls too. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt certainly he means the poor <hi>Jacobites</hi> (as they call them:) Well, I perceive that a <hi>Few</hi> of theſe are <hi>too Many,</hi> (for the <hi>Fewneſs</hi> of their Number is one Argument;) but it ſeems they cannot be contented to be a <hi>Few,</hi> but they muſt alſo be <hi>moſt unworthy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful,</hi> in not conſidering the large and ample Benefactions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them; by taking away from the <hi>Clergy</hi> their Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Livelihoods, and from the <hi>Laity</hi> their Places and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and for the additional Favour of paying <hi>double Taxes.</hi> One would think ſuch Obligations as theſe, ſhould make the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt among them a little more Senſible and Thankful. Archbiſhop <hi>Sancroft,</hi> I doubt, was one of the ungratefulleſt Men in the World for not taking Notice of the great Kindneſs Dr. <hi>John Tillotſon</hi> did him in Uſuping his Place, and Turning him out of his Houſe and Home. Was there ever ſuch <hi>ungrateful</hi> Men heard of? That when there is ſuch mighty Care taken to oblige them in this Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and to win them; and yet they are ſo Peeviſh, Stubborn, and Obſtinate, That they will neither <hi>Swear,</hi> nor keep <hi>Faſts,</hi> or <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings,</hi> nor make <hi>Addreſſes</hi> to ſtand by — with their Lives and Fortunes. Upon the whole therefore, I find theſe <hi>Jacobites</hi> are a very odd Sort of Folks: For firſt of all, They are <hi>Few</hi> in Number: Secondly, They are <hi>Blind</hi> and cannot ſee Providences, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59293:18"/>
themſelves, and forſake their Principles, as faſt as other People: And laſt of all, They are wretchedly <hi>Ungrateful,</hi> in being ſo very Fooliſh, as not to take the moſt real Injuries and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for the higheſt Obligations and Kindneſſes in the World.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhewed you their <hi>Satyr</hi> and <hi>Invectives;</hi> the next Branch of their Eloquence is <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> in which indeed they are not ſo Large and Copious, but full out as <hi>Fulſom,</hi> and <hi>void of Truth.</hi> I ſhall give you but an Inſtance or two, but by them you may judg of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, if you purpoſe to lay down a Foundation for future Greatneſs, you muſt be Wiſe, and begin betimes, and never ſtick at <hi>Flattering</hi> the Perſon you intend to riſe by, whatever his Merits or Performances are; for this ſhews your Inclination, as well as Ability, to ſerve a Cauſe. Thus, for Inſtance, you muſt tell the People at a <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> Sermon, That <note n="*">Dr. Tillotſon at Lincolns Inn, Jan. <hi>31. 1688.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This is the moſt illuſtrious Houſe of</hi> Naſſau <hi>and</hi> Orange, <hi>which God hath ſo highly honoured above all the Families of the Earth, to give a Check to the Two aſpiring Monarchs of the</hi> Weſt, <hi>and bold At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptors upon the</hi> Liberties <hi>of</hi> Europe: <hi>To the One in the laſt Age, and to the Other in the preſent. As if the Princes of this valiant and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Line had been of the Race of</hi> Hercules, <hi>born to reſcue Mankind from Oppreſſion, and to quell Monſters.</hi> How do you like this, Sir? It is thick and palpable, and you may even feel it: Such Stuff-might do pretty well in a <hi>Recorder's Speech,</hi> or from the Mouth of an <hi>Arche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> or a <hi>Killigrew;</hi> but from a <hi>Plump Divine,</hi> and out of the <hi>Pulpit</hi> too, 'tis abominably nauſeous, and turns the Stomach. Had he told that this <hi>Family</hi> had a Hand in the Revolutions of <hi>Europe,</hi> and fought, or run away, as they found Occaſion, Somebody or other might have believed it; but as he has laid it, 'tis <hi>meer Bounce,</hi> and incredible Rho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omantade, and, in truth, he plainly <hi>Banters</hi> his Heroe. What harm hath this <hi>illuſtrious Family</hi> done him, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd by him at this Rate? Had he nothing elſe to <hi>abuſe</hi> them with, but <hi>Hercules's</hi> and <hi>Monſters,</hi> and being <hi>Honoured above all the Families of the Earth?</hi> Commend me to the <hi>Nonconformiſt Woman;</hi> as the honeſter Preacher of the Two, who being deſirous to ſee a <hi>Great Prince,</hi> and being informed which was he, lift up her Hands with Admiration, and cried out, <hi>Good Lord! What great Things God can do by ſuch contemptible Means.</hi> But this, as it is groſs <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> ſo it is ſo very exact and punctual Flattery, as not to have one Word of Truth. For this Illuſtrious Houſe of Naſſau, as <hi>illuſtrious</hi> as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59293:19"/>
it is, has never yet been <hi>ſo far honoured</hi> to check the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in the laſt Age, nor the <hi>French</hi> King in this. And (as I take it) there is ſome difference between <hi>Quelling</hi> Monſters, and <hi>Breeding</hi> them. It is true, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was ſufficiently <hi>check'd</hi> and <hi>quell'd</hi> in the laſt Age; but this great Work was a little too illuſtrious for the <hi>Naſſau</hi>'s, or any of their Family. It was the famous Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who put a ſtop to the growth of that <hi>Monarch,</hi> by the Deſtruction of the <hi>Invincible Armada,</hi> and by ſeveral famous Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions into <hi>Spain</hi> it ſelf; and in good truth the <hi>Naſſau's,</hi> and the <hi>poor diſtreſſed States,</hi> had been probably ſwallowed up by that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, had it not been for the powerful Aſſiſtance both of Men and Money, which <hi>She</hi> gave them. And what I wonder made him forget Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in a Caſe ſo glaring and clear, that all the World knows it? Why Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had a long time been Dead and Buried; and to celebrate the Grave, though it be far the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſter and more generous way, yet it is but a cold Buſineſs, and will never edify. In the mean time, if he had not thought fit to be ſo juſt to her Memory, as to make an honourable mention of her, in a Caſe in which ſhe made ſuch a mighty Figure; he might however have been ſo juſt to Truth, as not to have <hi>wrong'd</hi> her, by aſcribing that Honour to another which was peculiarly her own: And eſpecially by aſcribing it to ſuch a <hi>Perſon,</hi> who was himſelf forced to take Shelter under her <hi>Protection;</hi> and whoſe then, and future Greatneſs, was in a great Meaſure, if not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, owing to her.</p>
            <p>And juſt ſuch another Piece of Truth is the Second Branch, of <hi>quelling</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King in this Age: I ſuppoſe by taking of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, Namur, Charleroy,</hi> and the two Battels of <hi>Steenkirk</hi> and <hi>Landen;</hi> theſe are terrible Inſtances of his being <hi>quell'd</hi> and <hi>cruſh'd</hi> for ever, and what he muſt expect when ſuch <hi>illuſtrious Families,</hi> and the Race of <hi>Hercules,</hi> undertakes him. But I muſt do this Author Right, all theſe Things have been done ſince he <hi>Preached</hi> and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed</hi> his Sermon: And therefore you are not to underſtand this as <hi>History,</hi> and <hi>matter of Fact;</hi> but this <hi>checking</hi> and <hi>quelling</hi> is Viſionary and Prophetick Language, expreſſing not what was done, but what would be done hereafter. In the mean time this Gentleman is very unlucky at <hi>telling of Fortunes,</hi> he had better have left this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince to his Friend St. <hi>A—ph,</hi> who poſſibly might have found Something in the <hi>Revelations;</hi> but all that I ſhall obſerve is, That there is a great difference between <hi>Propheſy</hi> and <hi>Flattery,</hi> the one is <hi>always</hi> true, the other <hi>never.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59293:19"/>The next Thing you may take Notice of, is uſher'd in with theſe Words,<note n="*">Dr. Tillotſon before the King and Queen, Octob. <hi>6. 1692.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Behold a Greater than He is here.</hi> And that his Auditory might be ſure not to miſtake him, he adds eight Lines af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>I ſay, Behold a Greater than He is here.</hi> Which in the firſt Place is a very <hi>Scandalous Uſe</hi> of Scripture Expreſſions; which ſhews what Reverence they have, when they can with ſuch aſſuming and reiterated Boldneſs apply theſe very Expreſſions to magnify a <hi>mortal Man,</hi> (and him none of the beſt in the World) which our Saviour himſelf us'd with reſpect to his own Perſon: But <hi>Flattery</hi> hath no Bounds, and there is nothing ſo Sacred, but muſt be preſs'd to ſerve it; and 'tis yet worſe by many Degrees to tranſlate them to ſuch a Cauſe, in which there is not one tittle of Grammatical Truth, even abſtracted from the Sacredneſs of the Expreſſions themſelves. For <hi>Greater</hi> is a Term of Compariſon, <hi>And greater than who is here?</hi> Why <hi>Greater</hi> than the <hi>French</hi> King. And are not you now abundantly ſatisfied that theſe Men will ſpeak nothing but plain and evident Truth in their Sermons? He may <hi>ſay it,</hi> and <hi>ſay it,</hi> as often as he pleaſe; but there is not one ſingle Man on the <hi>Earth</hi> who believes it, nor does he believe it himſelf. And eſpecially as he hath laid the Compariſon, for to make his own <hi>Heroe</hi> greater than him, he hath made the <hi>French</hi> King greater than in truth he is: For how Great do you think this Prince is? Thus you have it from the Doctor himſelf (<hi>ibid. p.</hi> 2. 8. <hi>&amp; ſeq.) A mighty Prince, who hath in Perfection all the Advantages — who, in the Opinion of ſome, hath paſſed for many Years for the moſt</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick, <hi>and</hi> Powerful, <hi>and</hi> Richeſt <hi>Monarch that hath appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in theſe Parts of the World for many Age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; who has Govern'd his Affairs by the deepeſt and ſteddieſt Councels, and moſt refin'd Wiſdom of this World A Prince Mighty and Powerful in his Preparations for War. Formidable for his vaſt and well diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Armies, and for his great Naval Force; and who hath brought the Art of War almoſt to that Perfection as to be able to Conquer, and do his Buſineſs, without Fighting; a Myſtery hardly known to former Age and Generations. And all this Skill and Strength United under One abſolute Will — Who commands the Eſtates of all his Subjects, and of all his Conqueſts, which hath furniſhed him with an almoſt inexhauſtible Treaſure and Revenue.</hi> Perhaps Sir, you think your ſelf at <hi>Paris,</hi> and this Gentleman is <hi>flattering</hi> and <hi>abuſing</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, as he does his own <hi>Maſter.</hi> But you are very much Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken; for this is for no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing elſe but to bring in Four or Five Words, <hi>Behold a Greater is here:</hi> That is, <hi>more Politick, Powerful</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59293:20"/>
               <hi>Rich,</hi> than the <hi>moſt Politick, moſt Powerful,</hi> and <hi>Richeſt</hi> Monarch in theſe parts of the World. And ſo it ſeems his Councels are <hi>deeper</hi> than the <hi>deepest, ſteddier</hi> than the <hi>ſteddiest,</hi> and ſo forth. Well, this is <hi>great</hi> indeed, who would have thought it? But there is one Thing a little more Natural, and that is <hi>Conquering without Fighting.</hi> This Art our <hi>Heroe</hi> muſt learn: For 'tis moſt certain that he muſt <hi>Conquer</hi> that way, or not at all; for he never yet was able to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer with Fighting.</hi> However, when Men are for Compariſons, they had as good do it to ſome Purpoſe. And when his Hand was in, he might have made him <hi>greater</hi> than all the <hi>Superlatives</hi> in the World; <hi>wiſer</hi> than the <hi>Wiſest, better</hi> than the <hi>Best, more righteous</hi> than the <hi>Juſteſt,</hi> and <hi>humbler</hi> than <hi>Humility</hi> it ſelf: For this might have been as ſoon ſaid, and as true as the reſt. And in truth he offers very fairly; for ſaith he, <hi>And who hath made it the great ſtudy and endeavour of his Life, to imitate theſe Divine Perfections, as far as the Imperfection of human Nature in this mortal State will admit, and one who never ſaid or did an inſolent Thing.</hi> And now is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any Man to expoſe ſuch <hi>nauſeous and rank Flattery</hi> ſpoken to a Man's Face, and printed by SPECIAL COMMAND, and which the Sermon and Publication is a direct and full Confutation of? For a Man of clear and ſteddy Vertue, can never have the Patience to hear himſelf thus daub'd over, and much leſs to <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize</hi> and <hi>Command</hi> the ſending his own undue and immoderate Praiſes round about the Kingdom. I do not know what Notions ſome Men may have of <hi>Modeſty,</hi> or whether they think it a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertue:</hi> However certainly it very well becomes <hi>Divines,</hi> and the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> And when they give themſelves up to <hi>laſh out</hi> in this manner, whether they advance other Mens Characters, to be ſure they <hi>reproach</hi> themſelves, and become the Scorn and Indignation of every wiſe and ſober Man. A flattering <hi>Buffoon</hi> is a ridiculous, mean, and contemptible Creature; but a <hi>flattering Divine ſtinks</hi> above Ground, and is nothing but <hi>Filth, Mire,</hi> and <hi>Dunghil,</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umes to choak and pollute the moſt Sacred Places and Exerciſes.</p>
            <p>I do not deny but there may be made tolerable uſe of <hi>Flattery</hi> it ſelf, in ſuch Caſes when Men are too big, and too untractable, for plain and down-right <hi>Admonition</hi> and <hi>Reproof;</hi> perhaps, in ſuch Caſes, it may not be amiſs for other <hi>Perſons</hi> beſides <hi>Divines,</hi> and for other <hi>Places</hi> beſides the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> to come at them as well as they can, and enter by that Door which is open. For Inſtance, poſſibly it might not be altogether unuſeful to tell a <hi>Great Prince,</hi> 
               <q>That he was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59293:20"/>
the <hi>Flower of Majeſty,</hi> the <hi>Splendor of the Crown,</hi> and the <hi>Fountain of all Princely Vertues:</hi> For that in the firſt place, being himſelf of the <hi>Race of Great Kings,</hi> and <hi>born</hi> to inherit the Throne of Three flouriſhing Kingdoms, he took no <hi>illegal</hi> and <hi>unnatural Steps</hi> to poſſeſs himſelf before the time; but ſtay'd till <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Laws,</hi> had, with all the Fairneſs in the World, put the <hi>Crown</hi> upon his Head. A Prince of that great <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> that a Throne was no Temptation to him; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d he be prevail'd to accept one that was not his <hi>Birthright<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> tho offered him by the <hi>greateſt Importunity</hi> by thoſe who had the moſt <hi>unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> Right to diſpoſe of it. Of that <hi>inflexible Juſtice,</hi> that a <hi>Flaw,</hi> or a <hi>Doubt,</hi> will make him ſtartle; and he looks upon thoſe as the worſt of Enemies, who would perſwade him to any Thing that is not infinitely clear in <hi>Point of Right.</hi> Of that <hi>tender Filial Piety,</hi> that being incorporated by Marriage into a <hi>Royal Family,</hi> he Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured his <hi>Wifes Father</hi> as his <hi>own;</hi> and has done him no more <hi>harm,</hi> than he would have done to his own <hi>dear Natural Parents</hi> upon the ſame Opportunities. One, who hath ſuch a mighty Veneration for <hi>Truth,</hi> that he ſcorns to <hi>ſlander</hi> a <hi>Turk,</hi> and much leſs his own <hi>Uncle</hi> or <hi>Father;</hi> that conſequently he hath made good, and punctually proved every Word of <hi>his</hi> Revolutional <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi> eſpecially relating to the Prince of <hi>W.</hi> by a thouſand Witneſſes. A Prince, in fine, of that Zeal for Religion, that he is mindful of all the TEN COMMANDMENTS, but hath an eſpecial Regard to the FIFTH, the NINTH, and the TENTH. What need I ſpeak of his <hi>Military</hi> Vertues, when by his pure Wiſdom and Conduct he hath ſaved whole Armies, <hi>Bag and Baggage</hi> and all; or of his Perſonal Valour, who always ſcorn'd to turn his Back upon any Enemies, and eſpecially the <hi>Puny</hi> and <hi>Cowardly French,</hi> but hath routed them with his very Looks.</q> Now, Sir, although there is not one Word of this ſtrictly and literally true, however it may have a Figurative uſe, and ſome good Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage may be made of a very bad Thing, to <hi>flatter</hi> Men out of the <hi>Vices</hi> which they have, and into the <hi>Vertues</hi> which they have not, when they cannot otherwiſe be dealt with. But the <hi>Flattery</hi> we are ſpeaking of, is quite another Thing; 'tis delivered from the <hi>Pulpit</hi> as Holy Language, and Sacred Oracles; and inſtead of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men to <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> 'tis deſign'd only to Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify than <hi>Vices,</hi> to Poliſh and Guild over the moſt enormous Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to Pamper a hard Conſcience, and to put a Theological <hi>Eucus</hi> on the deepeſt Crimes: That is, in the Prophet's Dialect. <hi>To
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59293:21"/>
call Evil Good, and Good Evil.</hi> To harden Men in their Sin, and ſow Pillows under their Elbows.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Sermon at the <hi>Temple, Dec.</hi> 30. which you muſt know was deſigned as a kind of <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> on the Death of the late great Lady at <hi>Kenſington;</hi> and this was not a Province taken up out of meer Choice, or ſingly allotted to him, but the univerſal Subject of all the Sermons in and about the Town for that Day. From whence you are given to underſtand, That this was by <hi>order</hi> and direction from their Superiors; and ſo you may take it, if you pleaſe, not for a Religious Commemoration, but a <hi>Politick</hi> one, to ſerve ſome <hi>Politick</hi> End of their <hi>Maſters,</hi> and perhaps of their own; and what thoſe Ends are you may eaſily ſee, and I ſhall juſt touch upon as I go along: And truly it looks as if their <hi>Inſtructions</hi> had been very particular, and the <hi>Heads</hi> upon which they ſhould diſcourſe aſſign'd them; for they all tell the ſame Tale, and almoſt in the ſame Words.</p>
            <p>However I am now upon the Doctor's <hi>Sermon,</hi> and what I have to remark to you is included in theſe Particulars. As, 1. The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter he gives the deceaſed Princeſs. 2. The Account he gives of Providence, in relation to her Death. 3. An Excurſion in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of an <hi>old Friend</hi> of his.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Character, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And here I ſhall do what theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men never knew how to do, if they thought it not for their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and that is, to ſpeak Modeſtly of the Dead; and therefore whatever <hi>Perſonal</hi> Vertues the Doctor, or any other, aſcribe unto her, I ſhall by no means meddle with: Let them therefore ſay what they pleaſe of her Charity, Affability, Diligence, and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Prayers, I ſhall never envy at theſe Characters, but hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh ſhe had all thoſe Vertues, and many more; but theſe are purely <hi>Perſonal,</hi> and concern neither <hi>Them</hi> nor <hi>Us.</hi> But there is an <hi>Action</hi> of hers which very nearly affects <hi>them,</hi> and which it highly concerns them to clear up as a Vertue, or at leaſt to make it Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; or elſe all her Vertues, if they were a Thouſand ſold more, will do them no good: But this they are either perfectly ſilent in, or mention it ſo very ſlightly and poorly, as if they were afraid to meddle with it; or as if it no way related to her Memory, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned themſelves. But theſe Gentlemen celebrate the Vertues of this <hi>Great Lady,</hi> as the Regicides and their Brood defame the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt; they load him with all the Vices they can think on, to juſtify their Rebelling againſt and Murthering of him: So theſe are full of her <hi>Praiſes,</hi> that they may vindicate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59293:21"/>
their taking an Oath of Allegiance to her: Whereas thoſe Things concern the Caſe neither of the one, nor the other. The ſingle Queſtion in which <hi>thoſe</hi> are concern'd, is not whether he was a <hi>Vicious</hi> King, but whether he was a <hi>Lawful</hi> one? So here, the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not whether ſhe was a <hi>Vertuous Woman,</hi> but whether ſhe was a <hi>Lawful Queen?</hi> And as to this Point there are ſeveral Things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our Obſervation; as.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are ſo far from conceiving that the <hi>Aſſuming the Crown</hi> was a <hi>Vertue</hi> in <hi>Her,</hi> that the <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> they pretend to Excuſe themſelves by, proceed upon the clean contrary Suppoſition. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> talks of nothing but the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of Uſurpation, the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of them that take the Government, and God's over-ruling the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of Men. He hath taken abundance of Pains, and ſaid all that he can, (and much more than is true) in his Two vile Books, to Excuſe the Wickedneſs of <hi>Swearing;</hi> but not one ſingle Word to <hi>vindicate</hi> his <hi>Powers</hi> from Wickedneſs, but ſuppoſes the direct contrary; and upon that Suppoſition frames all his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and Reaſons. A <hi>King de facto</hi> is another goodly <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis;</hi> and thoſe who are craz'd with this Notion, ſpend all their Arguments (ſuch as they are) to prove it Lawful to pay Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to ſuch a King; but not one of them ſays, or thinks, That 'tis <hi>Lawful</hi> to be a <hi>King de facto:</hi> And 'tis impoſſible they ſhould; for a <hi>King de facto</hi> is oppoſed (in their Senſe) to a <hi>King de jure;</hi> and a <hi>Lawful King de facto,</hi> is a Contradiction in the very Terms. 'Tis as if a Man ſhould ſay, Legal Illegality, Honeſt Villany, or Rightful Wrong; one of the Terms is a direct Contradiction to the other. <hi>Abdication,</hi> let that Word mean what it will, (for they are not <hi>yet</hi> fully agreed about it) can extend to none but the Perſon <hi>Abdicating;</hi> and therefore in an <hi>Hereditary Monarchy,</hi> the Right de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends to the next of the Line; and I ſuppoſe, by this time, all the World is ſatisfied of the Legitimacy of the <hi>Prince of Wales.</hi> So that let their <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> be what they will, they all ſit very heavy on her; and the Excuſes they make for themſelves, are but ſo many broad Accuſations of <hi>Her:</hi> For let <hi>force</hi> excuſe as much Submiſſion as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> pleaſes, it can never excuſe it ſelf: Let a <hi>King de facto</hi> warrant as many <hi>Oaths</hi> as they think fit, it can never warrant the invading and exerciſing an Authority which <hi>of Right</hi> belongs to another: Let <hi>Abdication</hi> juſtify the ſetting aſide one Prince, it can never juſtify the ſetting aſide another, who hath not <hi>Abdicated.</hi> So that turn their <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> which way you will, and grant them all they demand, They all load <hi>her,</hi> in this Point, as hard as the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59293:22"/>
               <hi>Jacobites,</hi> and make this Action highly Faulty by their own Principles. They are very induſtrious indeed to ſhake off all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice from themſelves, but then they do as induſtriouſly lay it at her Door: And any Man, who reads the numerous Pamphlets that have been wrote on this Occaſion, will find, That they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to lay all the Blame on her, and her Husband, that they may ſhift it from themſelves. And therefore Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> hath mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken his Compliment, which he ſo frankly beſtows upon <hi>ſome among our ſelves,</hi> in his laſt Sermon, (p. 15) <hi>Her greateſt and moſt implacable Enemies had no other Fault to charge her with, but her Throne:</hi> For it is the very <hi>fault</hi> that they themſelves charge her with, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can quit their Hands of it, They muſt <hi>grow Wiſer</hi> once more, and write <hi>new Caſes of Allegiance,</hi> and give ſome <hi>new Reaſons,</hi> for all the <hi>old Ones</hi> do it as plain as Words can do. And if this be a Sign of <hi>great</hi> and <hi>implacable</hi> Enmity, they muſt have the Honour among them; for let them <hi>Pray</hi> and <hi>Preach,</hi> and <hi>Swear</hi> never ſo much, I defy all the <hi>Jacobites</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> to charge her with more Faults on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, than they have done themſelves. And in truth, even in their <hi>funeral Sermons,</hi> where they have endeavoured to ſpeak the beſt they are able, They mention it ſo gingerly, that any Man may ſee they knew not what to ſay to it, nor how to let it alone; which is the next Thing I am to obſerve to you. <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When they mention her <hi>taking the Crown,</hi> they do it ſo nicely, and in ſuch a Manner, as plainly ſhews, That they think it requires an Excuſe and Apology, and will not admit of a Juſtification. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſays, (p. 13.) <hi>She was always grieved at the Occaſion of taking the Government, and as glad to Reſign it.</hi> And again, (p. 15.) <hi>She aſcended the Throne indeed before ſhe deſired it; but was thruſt into it, not by an haſty Ambition, but to ſave a ſinking Church and Kingdom.</hi> I ſhall leave every Man to believe the <hi>Truth</hi> of this as he pleaſes; but this ſtrongly proves that the Doctor thought there was ſomething in the Wind, which wanted his Rhetorick to make the beſt of it, which yet, with all his Skill, he is not able to clear up; but hath left a <hi>black</hi> Mark upon it, and ſtain'd it with great and evident Signs of Suſpicion: For let the <hi>Occaſion</hi> be what it will, let there be <hi>grief</hi> or no grief, Men do not uſe to be very <hi>glad</hi> to reſign any Thing, and much leſs a <hi>Throne,</hi> which they fairly and honeſtly come by; and if ſhe was ſo joyful to <hi>reſign</hi> the Crown, as this Gentleman would make us believe, I doubt, it will prove a Sign that ſhe her ſelf thought ſhe could not very innocently wear it. But to whom, I pray, was ſhe ſo glad to <hi>reſign</hi> it? Why, to her <hi>Father.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59293:22"/>
And if this was the Caſe, Why did not ſhe firſt Conſult him, and try whether there were any fair ways to ſave the Church and Kingdom, and preſerve the <hi>Crown</hi> upon her <hi>Father</hi>'s Head? This would have ſav'd her <hi>Father,</hi> and the Church and Kingdom too; and moreover would have <hi>ſaved</hi> her the Trouble of that terrible <hi>grief</hi> the Doctor talks on: Or why did not ſhe afterwards, when he had lain ſome Years in <hi>Exile</hi> and <hi>Affliction</hi> (which muſt needs augment her <hi>grief,</hi> if ſhe had any before, or any Spark of Duty to a tender Parent) endeavour to compoſe the Differences and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, and reconcile her <hi>Father</hi> to his Subjects, and his Subjects to him, to gratify her <hi>joy,</hi> and put an End to her <hi>grief?</hi> But this <hi>joy</hi> is a very fruitleſs and unactive Paſſion, and ſerves to talk on in <hi>funeral Sermons,</hi> but is good for nothing at all beſides. And I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive meer <hi>grief</hi> and <hi>averſion,</hi> and <hi>no deſire,</hi> operate more ſtrongly than all the Joy in the World: Nay, it ſeems, thoſe wonderful Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions operate the clean contrary way, (as every Thing elſe does in <hi>Uſurpation.</hi>) For, according to the Doctor, ſhe was grieved, and had no deſire to take the Crown, and yet ſhe took it, and kept it; ſhe was glad to reſign it, and made not the leaſt ſtep towards it: It ſeems, theſe <hi>Scepters</hi> and <hi>Crowns</hi> are nothing but Mortification from one end to the other; the Occaſion was <hi>grief,</hi> the Deſire to take it <hi>none at all;</hi> and to be depriv'd of it the only Comfort left in ſuch Caſes; the <hi>joy</hi> of <hi>reſigning</hi> it is very lamentable. And I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Gentlemen forgot to tell us of her <hi>Five Years</hi> ſevere Tryal and Affliction, and her incredible Patience under them: For in good truth, as grievous as they were, ſhe bore them handſomely, and the moſt critical and piercing Eye could ſee nothing outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but the greateſt Gaiety, Pleaſure, and Complacency imaginable: But perhaps the <hi>grief</hi> might be the greater being kept within, and becauſe no body could perceive it</p>
            <p>The next Thing the Doctor tells us, is, That <hi>ſhe was Thruſt into it:</hi> This is a Metaphor, and means it was by Compulſion, and againſt her Will. So that we are ſtill upon the <hi>diminiſhing</hi> Point; but this is an <hi>Apology</hi> with a <hi>Reflection</hi> in the Belly of it: For if the matter had been clearly and manifeſtly Juſt, what need is there of ſuch <hi>thruſting</hi> and <hi>force?</hi> Do Men offer violence to their Faculties when they do a very fair and honeſt Action, or (as ſome call it) a very great and glorious One? Well, but ſhe was thruſt into it to <hi>Save a ſinking Church and Kingdom.</hi> And ſuppoſe that, That is at the beſt but a <hi>good End,</hi> and if the <hi>Means</hi> be not as good as the End, the Action is ſtark nought; and the Doctor knows well enough,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59293:23"/>
There was a Perſon who thruſt out his Hand to <hi>ſave</hi> the <hi>Ark,</hi> but becauſe he had no Authority, it coſt him his Life, and by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Judgment of God himſelf. Princes perhaps may miſtake themſelves, and think themſelves qualified to <hi>ſave</hi> Churches and Kingdoms; but if they ſo far miſtake as to <hi>thruſt</hi> themſelves through the Bowels of their <hi>Parents</hi> to do this, I doubt they take a very wrong Courſe: And all the <hi>Savings</hi> he can think on, will not juſtify the Violation of the Laws of God, Nature, and Nations. The Doctor therefore ought firſt to have proved, at leaſt to have ſaid, (whether he could prove it or no) That it is very <hi>lawful</hi> for one Prince to ſeize and Patrimony and Inheritance of another: That 'tis very <hi>lawful</hi> for <hi>Children</hi> to turn their Parents out of Doors, and take their Revenues to themſelves: That 'tis very <hi>lawful</hi> to ſtigmatize and brand an <hi>Infant Prince</hi> as ſuppoſititious, contrary to their own Knowledge; and then it was time enough to talk of <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Deſigns,</hi> which no body knows but themſelves; whatever the Pretences may be to bring about thoſe <hi>Ends.</hi> For let them have as many <hi>Ends</hi> as they will, the Laws of God and Nature are too Sacred and Inviolable to be broken for any <hi>Ends,</hi> let them be good or bad, plain or myſterious; and no Man can honeſtly do it to <hi>ſave</hi> himſelf, and much leſs to <hi>ſave</hi> other Folks. And this is fine Doctrine for the <hi>Pulpit</hi> and <hi>Funeral Sermons:</hi> A Man may take another Man's Eſtate for the Good of the Tenants; and a Child may trample on the Neck of his Father, and ſend him a Begging, for the Benefit of the Family. However this ſhews that the Doctor is in great Perplexity, he would fain ſay ſomething, but cannot tell what: He hath raiſed an Objection, and leaves it juſt as he found it. <hi>Implacable Enemies, had no other Fault to charge her with but her Throne.</hi> To let <hi>Implacable,</hi> and <hi>Enemies</hi> alone, as being out of the Queſtion, it is certain <hi>that Fault ſhe was charged with,</hi> and by them who pretend to be her <hi>Friends</hi> too; and what hath the Doctor ſaid to remove it? Why the Anſwer is, <hi>She did not deſire it, She was thruſt into it,</hi> and <hi>She had a very good End.</hi> And what then? Will any of theſe, or all together, change the vicious Nature of moral Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Will a Thing <hi>materially</hi> Evil become <hi>exceeding</hi> Good, from any Reluctances, Impulſes, or Deſigns of Men? This is not to make God's Law, but human Paſſions and Devices, the Rule and Standard of Vertue and Vice. So that this is a <hi>Fault,</hi> and will be a <hi>Fault</hi> ſtill, for any Thing the Doctor hath ſaid to the contrary: And theſe implacable People are at Liberty to charge her with what they pleaſe in this Point; for the Doctor hath not one ſingle
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59293:23"/>
Word to ſtop their Mouths. However, it muſt be owned that this is very ſeaſonable and faſhionable Divinity, and will ſerve all Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes as well as this. For inſtance; ſuppoſe any Man (impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable or placable it matters not) ſhould charge it as a <hi>Fault</hi> on Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> for taking the <hi>Oath:</hi> The Anſwer is plain, and at hand, For firſt, <hi>He did not deſire it;</hi> well, that will be granted: Secondly, He was <hi>thruſt upon it;</hi> and that I ſuppoſe will be granted too: And laſt of all, He did it out of a good and <hi>ſaving End;</hi> for to <hi>ſave</hi> Preferments, or to advance them, will be allowed to be a good End. And therefore the Concluſion is plain, That 'tis very lawful to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> let the matter of it be what it will. In the mean time as to the <hi>Matter</hi> of this Action of <hi>taking</hi> the <hi>Throne,</hi> the Doctor hath not one Word to ſay to it, and leaves the People to judge as they pleaſe of it; which notwithſtanding is the only Thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which a Caſuiſt can pronounce and determine: For <hi>Deſign's</hi> and <hi>Ends</hi> are ſecret Things, and are moſt commonly the very <hi>worſt</hi> when the <hi>beſt</hi> is pretended. <hi>Cromwel</hi> could <hi>pray,</hi> and <hi>preach</hi> too, in great abundance; and (if you will believe him) He did not <hi>deſire the Government,</hi> but was <hi>thruſt upon it to ſave a ſinking Kingdom,</hi> (as he tells them expreſly in a Speech to his Parliament.) And here are two very <hi>hideous</hi> and black Circumſtances which <hi>Cromwel</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wanted, That in thoſe days there was not a <hi>Natural Father</hi> in the Caſe. Nor Secondly, The moſt <hi>kind and indulgent Father</hi> in the World. And therefore commend me to Dr. <hi>Wake,</hi> who ſpeaks a little more plainly in <hi>his Funeral Sermon,</hi> (p. 19.) She was <hi>ſo great a Lover of her Country, and the Intereſt of it, as to be willing to hazard what next her Conſcience ſhe moſt valued, her good Name, and good Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the World, for the Preſervation of them.</hi> So that it ſeems the Buſineſs was not very <hi>reputable</hi> by his own Account; for 'tis ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to talk of <hi>hazarding of a good Name, and good Opinion,</hi> if the Thing it ſelf, in its own Nature, had been of <hi>good Fame and Report;</hi> and therefore the Doctor plainly gives up the Cauſe in this Point. The Action it ſelf was neither <hi>honourable</hi> nor <hi>praiſe worthy;</hi> for if it had, the performing of it would have been a means to gain a <hi>good Name and Opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and not to <hi>hazard</hi> it. The Doctor indeed min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the matter, and ſpeaks ſoftly, but the plain Engliſh of his Words is, That it is <hi>Infamous:</hi> And the Reputation and Vertues of a Prince are ſo nearly link'd together, that 'tis impoſſible to part them; and whatſoever is <hi>infamous</hi> in a Prince, I doubt is vicious too. So that here we have a pretty fair Confeſſion, although it is finely dreſſed up; that the People might not perceive it. It would have looked
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59293:24"/>
a little ankwardly, when a Man had been ſtretching his Wits and Eloquence to ſay the <hi>beſt</hi> Things he was able, to daſh all with a Couple of <hi>blunt</hi> and <hi>uncourtly</hi> Expreſſions; She loved her Country ſo dearly, as to be <hi>unnatural and ungrateful</hi> to her Parents: But the Doctor is a Courtier, and knows Language better than ſo; and therefore it is to be let down in a genteel and mannerly Dialect, only She <hi>hazarded a good Name and Opinion in the World.</hi> But <hi>Things</hi> are the ſame, let the Expreſſions be what they will: Let him call it, if he pleaſe, <hi>hazarding a good Name,</hi> and then tell us what he means by that, or in what Inſtances ſhe run that <hi>hazard,</hi> and he ſays the very ſame Thing, and will talk like a malicious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable <hi>Jacobite.</hi> In the mean time theſe Gentlemen have as little conſulted their own <hi>Reputation</hi> as hers; for if the taking the Crown was an Action that <hi>hazarded her good Name,</hi> the praying for, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, and abetting her in that Action, muſt alſo <hi>hazard their good Names;</hi> for whoever partakes of an <hi>infamous</hi> Action, partakes of the <hi>Infamy</hi> too: And ſo theſe Gentlemen have ſtrained their Rhetorick to much purpoſe, to give ſuch an honourable Character of themſelves, as they have done of her. I hope hereafter they will not take it ſo heinouſly, if Men think they have <hi>hazarded</hi> their <hi>good Names and Reputations;</hi> for why ſhould any Body have a better Opinion of them, than they have of themſelves?</p>
            <p>Since the firſt Impreſſion of this, Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> hath undertaken the Argument, and hath publiſhed a Pamphlet, called, <hi>An Eſſay on the Memory of the late Queen:</hi> This <hi>Doctor</hi> you know is a Man of mighty <hi>Latitude,</hi> and can ſay any Thing to ſerve a Turn; whoſe <hi>Reverence</hi> reſolves Caſes of Conſcience backwards and forwards, diſputes <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> praiſes and diſpraiſes by ſecular Meaſures; with whom Vertue and Vice, Paſſive Obedience and Rebellion, Paricide and Filial Duty, Treachery and Faithfulneſs, and all the Contradictions in Nature, are the <hi>beſt</hi> or the <hi>worſt</hi> Things under the Sun, as they are for his Purpoſe, and according as the Wind ſits: Who equally and indifferently writes <hi>for</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> all Men, the Goſpel, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too, as the World goes: Who can beſtow a Panegyrick upon the Seven Deadly Sins, and (if there be occaſion,) can make an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective againſt all the Commandments. Now, Sir, you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, That is a very hard Caſe indeed, which a Man of ſuch a <hi>Breadth</hi> and Qualifications cannot ſpeak plainly to, and does not know what to do with. And thus you have him delivering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this Point, (p. 91.) <hi>In thoſe great Steps of her later Years, that carried a Face which at firſt Appearance ſeemed liable to Cenſure; and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59293:24"/>
that were the ſingle Inſtances of her whole Life, that might be thought capable of hard Conſtructions.</hi> You ſee, Sir, what a rare Faculty our <hi>Doctor</hi> hath at palliating and daubing: But you are not at all to wonder at this; for the moſt flagitious Crimes in the World, if our Author can find his Account in them, by a little turn of ungodly Rhetorick, ſhall be diminiſhed into nothing but <hi>Faces</hi> and <hi>Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances,</hi> and I cannot tell what. In the mean time he plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the Cauſe he deſigns to maintain; for it ſeems the matter is not ſo very clear, but it is encumber'd with criminal <hi>Seemings</hi> and <hi>Appearances.</hi> And what then, on God's Name, makes them talk over and over, and tell the World of the <hi>manifeſt</hi> Juſtice, and <hi>appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> Righteouſneſs of their Cauſe, when, according to their own Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, it carries the <hi>Face</hi> and <hi>Appearance</hi> of Guilt? For, as I take it, <hi>manifeſt</hi> Righteouſneſs, and <hi>ſeeming</hi> Unrighteouſneſs, is a manifeſt Contradiction. And what makes them clamour ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly againſt the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> for ſeeing the Revolution by ſuch a Light which they own it hath the <hi>Seeming</hi> and <hi>Appearance</hi> of? Or for thinking of Things in ſuch a manner which they themſelves ſay they <hi>may be thought capable of?</hi> However, the Doctor would have done but honeſtly, if he had told us the Grounds of theſe <hi>Faces</hi> and <hi>Appearances,</hi> and what are the Reaſons why this Action is <hi>liable to Cenſure, and capable of hard Conſtructions:</hi> And then the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der would have judged, whether it was only <hi>ſeeming</hi> and <hi>apparent,</hi> or real and in truth. But he durſt not truſt his Reader with telling him, That theſe Reaſons were drawn from the <hi>common Principles of human Nature, the conſtant Tenor and Declaration of Chriſtianity, the particular Direction of the Fifth and of the Tenth Commandment.</hi> Now 'tis a little too much for any Man but the Doctor, to call the noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and perſevering Violation of all, and every one of theſe, meer <hi>Faces,</hi> and <hi>Appearances,</hi> and <hi>ſeemingly</hi> Cenſurable; and, I doubt, ſo long as the Senſe of theſe remain in the World, it will not only be <hi>thought capable of hard Conſtructions,</hi> but incapable of any other. However the Doctor further tells us, (p. 93.) That <hi>ſhe ſaw that not only her own Reputation might ſuffer by it, but that Religion too, might be concerned in thoſe Reproaches that ſhe was to look for.</hi> How can that be, Sir, according to the magnificent Character that you, and the reſt of you, have given of it heretofore? For when you made it the Subject of your <hi>flattering Sermons,</hi> you uſed to extol it, as the greateſt, moſt glorious, and pious Action, that e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er was: And I hope ſuch Actions as theſe have no bad Influence either upon. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, or Religion, but the clean contrary; ſo that if ſhe her
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59293:25"/>
ſelf had ſuch a Senſe of it, it is plain ſhe did not believe you, but took her Sentiments from better Inſtructors, and from the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of that Religion ſhe was Educated in. And this you confirm as much as you can, when you immediately add, <hi>This was much more to her than all the Crowns could offer inſtead of it.</hi> Now, Sir, I hope you do not intend to perſwade the World, That ſhe valued the Opinion or Reproaches of the <hi>Jacobites</hi> more than the Crown; that therefore theſe Sentiments were raiſed not from particular and accidental Conſideration, but from the Nature of the Thing, and the general Senſe of Mankind about it. The Action, in its own Nature, was neither <hi>Reputable</hi> nor <hi>Righteous,</hi> and conſequently would reflect both upon her <hi>Reputation</hi> and her <hi>Religion:</hi> For 'tis impoſſible for any Man to think, That doing a Thing <hi>highly Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> will endanger Reputation, but advance it: That performing an Action of <hi>heroick Vertue</hi> and Piety will <hi>reproach</hi> Religion, but bring an Honour to it. So that at laſt the Doctor hath made a fair Commendation, and ſaid much in juſtification of his Cauſe, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting us that ſhe her ſelf had no very good Opinion of it, as ſeeing that both her own Reputation, and the Credit of Religion, might ſuffer by it. And this is yet further confirm'd, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation he makes of her intolerable Grief and Agonies, <hi>That ſhe made a Sacrifice of her ſelf in accepting that Elevation, which perhaps was harder for her to bear, than if ſhe had been made a Sacrifice in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereſt Senſe;</hi> that the Concealment of her Sorrow <hi>was more ſenſible and violent to her, than any Thing that could have been wiſhed her, by the moſt enraged and virulent of all her Enemies.</hi> (p. 96.) Now as to the <hi>Truth</hi> of this I will not diſpute with the Doctor; if any Man has a mind to believe it upon his bare Word, he may do as he pleaſe: But it was a hard Caſe, that all the <hi>flattering Sermons</hi> ſhe frequently heard, and the daily Converſe ſhe had with ſuch Men; could give her no eaſe. However (if this was the Caſe) it is ſure no extraordinary proof of the wonderful Glory and Bleſſedneſs of the Cauſe: Men do not uſe to live under eternal Crucifixions and Mortifications for doing the beſt Actions in the World. I doubt the Path was not ſo plain and clear, but there were Rubs in the way, which could not fairly be got over; the <hi>Duty to Parents,</hi> and <hi>the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of taking what is none of our own,</hi> are Points that will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be weather'd: And if (as the Doctor ſays) this mighty Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row aroſe from the <hi>Duty</hi> ſhe bore to her <hi>Father,</hi> there was no other way in the World to relieve her, and give her true Quiet, but by ſhewing that either ſhe was was wholy abſolved from that <hi>Duty;</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59293:25"/>
or that this Action was <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with it. But neither of theſe could be done. And this is a Point that always hath, and always will lye upon their hands; and they never ſpoke one Word to it, to give her ſolid Peace in the time of her Life, nor to clear her from the Imputation after her Death. But as then, ſo now, they are all for telling flattering and daubing Stories, and rambling from the true and direct Queſtion, which they dare not touch with one of their Fingers: Juſt as the Doctor here, (p. 32.) <hi>That the publick Good of Mankind, the Preſervation of Religion, and thoſe real Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to which Matters were driven, ought to ſuperſede all other Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Yes, I ſuppoſe, to <hi>ſuperſede</hi> the <hi>Fifth Commandment, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Duty, and common Juſtice.</hi> At this rate a Man may rob, and murther, or do any Thing to preſerve Religion, if Matters are come to Extremity: For I would fain ſee a Reaſon, why the ſame Occaſions would not ſuperſede all the Commandments, as well as one of them? The Doctor goes on, <hi>She had generous Notions of the Liberty of human Nature, and the Ends of Government, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to make Mankind happy and ſafe, and not to raiſe Power upon the Ruins of Property and Liberty; nor could ſhe think that Religion was to be delivered up to the Humours of miſguided Princes.</hi> Very good, Sir; but are there no <hi>Notions</hi> in the World, beſides the <hi>Notions of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of human Nature?</hi> Sure the Notions of the <hi>Obligations</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreints</hi> of human Nature are as conſiderable, and deſerve as much to be comply'd with; and no Man can juſtify the vindicating the Liberty of human Nature to others, by deſtroying the Reſtreints of it that God hath laid upon our ſelves: And, as I take it, 'tis no very honeſt Method for a Man to ſet himſelf, or others free, by knocking his Father on the Head. Let the <hi>Ends of Government</hi> be what they will, the Ends of <hi>Filial Piety,</hi> and commutative Juſtice, are every way as Sacred, and ought not to be tore up by the Roots, to make another Perſon anſwer the Ends of Government. <hi>Religion is not to be delivered up to the Humours of miſguided Princes;</hi> nor to the Humours of any Man elſe, though he calls himſelf a Biſhop; nor can be, except Men pleaſe themſelves: But for all that, I do not think the external Preſervation of Religion ought to be attempted by <hi>breaking the Commandments.</hi> However, at laſt he tells us, (p. 34) <hi>That being the only viſible Mean left to preſerve the Proteſtant Religion, ſhe was thereby determin'd to it.</hi> Well, if that were the only <hi>viſible Mean,</hi> then it ought to have been left to God's Providence; for that <hi>viſible Mean</hi> was ſtark nought, and can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be juſtified, as being a <hi>viſible</hi> Violation of that Religion it is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59293:26"/>
pretended to preſerve. For God never gave Authority, or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, to Children to turn their Parents out of Doors, and ſeize their Inheritance to themſelves.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, you ſee what kind of Divinity we have from theſe Men; they are very copious and full of Tales, about <hi>Ends and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, publick Good and Preſervations,</hi> which is always the Guiſe of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors,</hi> to conſecrate material Wickedneſs with holy Ends, which muſt commute and attone for all the Unrighteouſneſs they have dipt their Hands in. They know well enough there are <hi>three</hi> Things that neceſſarily and eſſentially concur to the Goodneſs of every Action; that the <hi>Matter</hi> of it be <hi>Juſt,</hi> the <hi>Meanes Lawful,</hi> and the <hi>End Right;</hi> but 'tis the <hi>laſt</hi> only they bedeck with Titles and Epithets; but the other Two are left to ſhift for themſelves, which notwithſtanding are the only Things that come under Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For <hi>Ends and Purpoſes</hi> are Myſteries and Secrets, and lodge in every Man's private Breaſt, and are frequently as various as the Men are that are engaged in the ſame outward Action. As in the Revolution, one Man's <hi>End</hi> might be to get a <hi>Throne,</hi> another's to gratify his <hi>Revenge,</hi> a third to feed his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> by patching up a crakt Fortune, or making a new one; a fourth to humour his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Inconſtancy; and of ſome, perhaps, the Ambition of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>King-makers:</hi> Now theſe are all perſonal, and every Man muſt anſwer for himſelf, and no Man can be party to another Man's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; but the outward Action, and the Means of attaining and ſupporting, they are all more or leſs concerned, and reſponſible. And one would think ſomething ſhould be ſaid a little to clear and ſmooth this; and not leave it to the mercy of every <hi>hard hearted Jacobite</hi> to worry them with at his Pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not the leaſt obſervable, That theſe Gentlemen ſhould with ſo much Care depreciate the Perſon they are celebrating, and fly in their own Faces. Common Diſcretion, one would think, ſhould have taught them to let this Point alone, if they had no more to ſay for it, but what reflects upon her and themſelves; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince ſome of it is apparently Falſe. What ſhould make Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> talk of <hi>Grief, and having no Deſire,</hi> and being <hi>Thruſt</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Throne, when every Man in <hi>England</hi> who ever ſaw the Court can conſute him, and the Nature of the Thing it ſelf conſutes him beyond Contradiction? For when a Princeſs hath broken through all the Sacred Bonds of Religion, Juſtice, and Humanity; when ſhe has driven over the Head of the beſt of Fathers to get into a Throne; to talk of <hi>Grief,</hi> and <hi>Averſion,</hi> and <hi>Compulſion</hi> is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59293:26"/>
the height of Paradox and Madneſs, and ſhews only what ſome Men will ſay to ſerve a Purpoſe: But what <hi>purpoſe</hi> was this to ſerve? That is no hard Queſtion to anſwer; for you find this was one, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot a main Branch of their <hi>Inſtructions:</hi> For they all have it more or leſs, and I am told it was not forgot in moſt of the Sermons of that Day. And by this time you may ſee through the Myſtery; It was a ſeaſonable Doctrine, and deſigned as a Document or Admonition to <hi>Princeſs Ann,</hi> or at leaſt to the People concerning <hi>her:</hi> For, Sir, you know, That in the Judgment of Nine parts of the Kingdom, ſhe hath a better Title to the Crown than another certain Perſon; and we want not Inſtances in this Kingdom of <hi>Poſſeſſion,</hi> and <hi>de Facto,</hi> giving Place to <hi>Right,</hi> by the Determination of an <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> and the Concurrence of all the People. And therefore if you would underſtand theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen right, you muſt interpret them in this manner,— <q>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, your Siſter had great <hi>Grief</hi> when ſhe took the Throne, and had no Will to it, and it was not very <hi>reputable</hi> neither; and therefore it is far better for you to conſult your own Credit and Eaſe, than to raiſe any Pretenſions, which will only multiply your Sorrow, and withal blaſt your Reputation. Beſides, ſhe was <hi>thruſt into it to ſave a ſinking Church and Kingdom;</hi> and that matter is taken Care of already, and in the Hands of another, and therefore you can have no ſuch Pretences. Furthermore, it is not impoſſible but your <hi>Brother</hi> may have a mind to Marry, and this might ſpoil his Fortunes; and therefore moſt certainly 'twas <hi>Grief, Unwillingneſs,</hi> and <hi>Hazarding her good Name in the World.</hi> And who, that is not abandon'd to the utmoſt neglect of themſelves, would (in ſuch a Caſe) meddle with ſuch <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful</hi> and <hi>hazardous</hi> Things?</q> And thus, Sir, you have the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery unfolded, and the Politick End of all this talk laid open. They could eaſily, if they had pleaſed, have celebrated this Action with the Epithets of <hi>Meritorious, Glorious, Godlike,</hi> and have put it into the ſame Dialect with the reſt of her Praiſes; (and I defy any Man to think that they were reſtrained by Religion or Conſcience) but it was not ſo convenient at this Time: That might have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Temptation to others, who had as good and the very ſame Pretenſions with her ſelf; and therefore it was fit to add a Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Diſcouragement, and mingle it at this Juncture with <hi>Sorrow, Violence,</hi> and <hi>Diſcredit.</hi> From whence you plainly ſee, what good Friends theſe Gentlemen are to the old <hi>Engliſh Monarchy.</hi> For moſt certainly the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of <hi>Abdication,</hi> with all its Branches, is now
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59293:27"/>
fallen to the Ground; for let <hi>Deſertion,</hi> or what they will, be <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication;</hi> and let the <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> be what they pleaſe, the plain Conſequence of this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is, That by the Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh Monarchy,</hi> ſhe aſcended the Throne in her own Right, and her Husband governed in Right of her; but then that Right is determined with her, and is now no more; and by the undoubted Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, that Right deſcends to the next Heir. And the ſingle Queſtion is no more but this; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe ſat upon the Throne of her Anceſtors? If ſhe did, then her Husband is no more her Heir than King <hi>Philip</hi> was Heir to Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> If ſhe did not, then the Conſtitution is broken to Pieces; our old <hi>Engliſh Monarchy</hi> is utterly aboliſhed and deſtroyed, and there is not the leaſt Footſtep of it remaining. But <hi>Monarcy</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Dutch,</hi> 'tis all one to them, they muſt follow their <hi>Inſtructions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. There is one Thing yet behind concerning this Action of <hi>aſſuming the Throne,</hi> which deſerves your Obſervation: And that is, That theſe Gentlemen have not given us <hi>the laſt Sentiments</hi> that ſhe her ſelf had of it Had there been a <hi>Death-bed Declaration,</hi> we might have believed ſhe had been in good Earneſt, though as ſtrangely and unaccountably Miſtaken as ever Perſon was: And to be ſure, had there been the leaſt Tittle of this, we ſhould have had it rung through the Kingdom, to fortify their Cauſe: But the induſtrious Concealment of every Thing that ſhe ſaid relating to this, is a Demonſtration that ſhe ſaid nothing to their Advantage, but the contrary. Here was an Action that alarm'd the World, ſtain'd the Glory of her Life, and (if Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> may be believ'd) was <hi>Grief</hi> and <hi>Sorrow</hi> to her ſelf; and 'tis next to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible but ſhe muſt ſay ſomething of this, when ſhe had a viſible Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her Death. A meer natural Conſcience, without the Light of Religion, muſt needs both inform and awaken her; and indeed there are broad Whiſpers as if ſhe had ſaid ſomething that was not very grateful to them. If theſe Gentlemen knew nothing of it, their Ignorance will excuſe them; but if they did, 'tis horrid Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy to conceal it. It ſeems they were acquainted with the manner of her Dying; Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> (p. 24) ſaith, <hi>She ſaw Death approaching without Fear, and prepared to receive the Stroke with Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp;c. <hi>which nothing could give but an innocent Conſcience.</hi> And Dr. <hi>Wake,</hi> (p. 35.) That for the <hi>Clearneſs of her Conſcience</hi> his Two Arguments are; <hi>The Eaſineſs of her own Mind in her Life time and her appearing unconcerned as the proſpect of her Death which</hi> (ſaith he)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59293:27"/>
               <hi>gave a final Evidence that ſhe accounted her ſelf prepared for it.</hi> So that here is no <hi>Fact</hi> but <hi>Reaſoning,</hi> and Concluſions drawn from Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes; and 'tis extreamly ridiculous to run to Inferences and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, if they could have proved it by plain Words from her own Mouth. 'Tis therefore undeniable, either that ſhe ſaid nothing at all, which is one of the ſtrangeſt Things in the World, or that which ſhe did ſay, is directly againſt them; and the great Care to ſuppreſs it, is as great an Evidence of it, as ſuch a Thing is capable of. And here we have the Difference between the <hi>two Cauſes</hi> in the trying Article of <hi>Death:</hi> On the one Side, We have Two <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> and <hi>Reverend Biſhops,</hi> beſides ſeveral others, who have given the higheſt Evidence of their intire Satisfaction in their Principles and Practices, by venturing their Souls in the ſame bottom with them, and with their laſt Breath declaring it in the moſt ſolemn Manner, and in the plaineſt Words. On the other Side, There is firſt one of their greateſt Biſhops dying without the leaſt mention of the Cauſe, although he himſelf had as great a Share in it, as half a Score of ſome others. And then the Death-bed of the Principal her ſelf, carries evident Suſpitions of the clean contrary. And the Concluſion from theſe Premiſſes, and the Application and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Point is this; <hi>Let my Soul dwell with thoſe Principles, which though they may create me Trouble and Affliction while I Live, yet I ſhall not be aſhamed of them when I come to Die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The next Thing is, The Account and Reaſon he gives of <hi>Providence,</hi> with reſpect to her Death. And of this he tells us, (p. 23, 24.) That though <hi>we do not know the particular Reaſons, yet there are general Anſwers which may ſatisfy:</hi> And his Anſwers are Two. One <hi>with reſpect to our ſelves; That God is Angry, and by the untimely Death of an Excellent Princeſs threatens his Judgments, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we Repent.</hi> The other is with reſpect to her; and then the Anſwer is, 'Tis <hi>no Loſs to change an Earthly Crown for an Heavenly Crown.</hi> Theſe are Reaſons I ſhall neither diſpute nor meddle with; but there is another, and a very <hi>particular</hi> one too, which the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor might have ſeen, if he had pleaſed, and which certainly would never have eſcaped him on any other Occaſion. The Queſtion (as he puts it himſelf) is concerning her <hi>ſudden and untimely Death,</hi> and being <hi>cut off in the Vigor and Strength of Age.</hi> And has the Doctor never heard of <hi>Rebellious and Diſobedient Children</hi> not living out half their Days? I ſhall not undertake to give any Reaſons for this, or any other Providence, which Providence it ſelf does not plainly and manifeſtly direct to: That is enough for the Doctor to do, who hath made
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59293:28"/>
more bold with Providence than ever Man did. But when there is a <hi>Commandment,</hi> to which a Promiſe of <hi>long Life</hi> is particularly and expreſly annexed, which plainly implies a <hi>Threatning</hi> of a <hi>ſhort Life</hi> upon the <hi>Violation</hi> of it: And when the Fact is Notorious and Manifeſt, and a viſible Providence following it, punctually, and in all Points anſwering the Divine Threatnings; I am certain a Man may with more Safety and Modeſty aſſign that as a Reaſon, which God himſelf in particular threatens to that particular Fact. This is not entring into God's Secrets, but following the Conduct of his Commandments; and interpreting his Providences, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe Declarations which God himſelf hath made in that very Caſe. And I do not at all doubt to ſay, That here was as great and open a Breach of the <hi>FIFTH COMMANDMENT</hi> as ever was in the World, aggravated by many and heinous Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; as unnatural Ingratitude, triumphing and perſevering in it for a long time: And all the Commendations theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men give of her great Knowledge, Vertue, and Piety, are but as ſo many more Aggravations; as thereby acting againſt a clearer Light, and bringing a greater Diſhonour and Scandal upon the Chriſtian Religion and Profeſſion. However, this is the very Caſe to which God threatens ſhortneſs of Life; and here we have the Matter of that Threatning plainly exemplified in the untimely Death of this Princeſs: But whether or no, in this ſevere Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, her undutifulneſs to her Parents hath overtaken her, or whether God hath cut her off in the midſt of her Days for this, or for any other wiſe and juſt Reaſon; I am very certain that from hence there are two Things of practical Obſervation, and which (with theſe Gentlemens good leave) deſerve to be inculcated to the People on this ſolemn Occaſion, and as uſeful at leaſt as any Thing they have ſaid in their Sermons.</p>
            <p>The one is, That from hence Children be admoniſhed to be more <hi>dutiful to their Parents,</hi> leſt their Lives alſo are ſhortned, and they for their Diſobedience cut off from the Earth in the Flower of their Age. Theſe Gentlemen indeed have taken the contrary Method, and (as far as in them lies) have tore up by the Roots all Filial Piety: For if a Perſon, living in the conſtant and plain Violation of this Duty, may notwithſtanding be magnified to the utmoſt ſtretch of Mens Wits and Underſtandings, may be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended from the Pulpit as a great Examplar of all Vertue, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and Excellence; and preached up into Heaven by a whole Sett of Divines, without the leaſt guard on this Head, or any
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59293:28"/>
manner of direction concerning it; I doubt rebellious Children will infer for themſelves, and think they may merit abundance of Praiſe too, and go to Heaven at laſt, although they allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a viſible and ſtanding Breach of a plain and neceſſary Duty. For if unnatural Diſobedience be no Impeachment to one Man's Vertue, neither is it to another's; and God hath not given the Fifth Commandment to common People only, and left Princes to their own Liberty in the matter. And, in good truth, theſe Gentlemen have been ſuch faithful Stewards, as to do their beſt to pray and preach all natural Duty out of the World. And therefore</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, To Caution all Men from hence to be very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful how they join with, encourage, ſupport or commend (direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or by conſequence) any Diſobedience to Parents; leſt the Fate of rebellious Children be derived to them, and they alſo ſhorten their own Days, and bring themſelves to an untimely End. For 'tis a rul'd Caſe, whoſoever is Acceſſary to the Guilt, is Acceſſary to the Puniſhment too. One Man's perſonal Vices become ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's by his Conſent and Approbation, and much more by his Applauding and Encouraging them. How large and wide there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Crime of Filial Diſobedience reaches, I ſhall not need to determine; ſo far as this Conſent extends to particular Perſons, the Guilt is Perſonal; and ſo far as it is National, the Guilt alſo is National; and the Threatning and Judgment is alſo as large, and as extenſive, as the Guilt. And there is a Shortning the Days of a Nation, as well as of particular Perſons, by cutting them off from being no more a People, or by diveſting them of their Ancient Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Conſtitution, Privileges, Laws and Franchiſes; which is in truth making them another Nation than they were before, and of another Polity. I pray God divert his Judgments both from particular Perſons, and from the whole Nation, and give all Men Wiſdom to take early Warning by <hi>particular Examples;</hi> that by a timely Repentance they may prevent the Execution of thoſe Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which apparently hang over our Heads, and are the declar'd Conſequences and Effects of our preſent Actions. For there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more plain than that this Nation hath notoriouſly violated the <hi>Fifth Commandment,</hi> upon all Accounts upon which it can be violated; both in an unjuſt Rebellion againſt the <hi>Civil Parent,</hi> and withal at the ſame time abetting and ſupporting an unparallel'd Diſobedience againſt the <hi>Natural Parent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Providence;</hi> There are ſome Circumſtances yet to be obſerv'd, particularly as to Time, and eſpecially if we ſhall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59293:29"/>
follow theſe Gentlemen in their Method of reading and interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Providence;</hi> and how much ſuch Obſervations will come home to them, you may ſee by this one Inſtance of Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi>
               <note n="*">Thankſgiving Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>1688.</hi> p. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Our wonderful Deliverance</hi> (ſays he) <hi>from the formidable</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Invaſion deſigned againſt us, happen'd in the Year</hi> 1588. <hi>And now juſt a hundred Years after, the very ſame Year, and at the ſame Seaſon of the Year, this laſt great Deliverance came to us. That horrid Gun-powder Conſpiracy, without Preſident, and without Parallel, was deſigned to have been executed upon the Fifth Day of</hi> November, <hi>the ſame Day upon which his Highneſs the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>Landed the Forces here in</hi> England, <hi>which he brought hither for our reſcue.</hi> And the very ſame you may find in Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> and others, mentioning it with mighty Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, as a Divine Seal and Teſtimony to their Cauſe Now, Sir, if you pleaſe turn your Eyes to the Caſe before us, and you will find, That the Princeſs ſickned, was invaded by a mortal Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſtruggled with the Grief and Pangs of it, in the ſame Month, Days and Moments, in the which her Father, but Six Years before, laboured under the Agonies of an unnatural Invaſion and Rebellion. That ſhe <hi>died</hi> the <hi>ſame Month,</hi> almoſt the ſame Day of the Month, but the very <hi>ſame Hour</hi> of the Day, on which her Father was forced into Exile, (for he withdrew himſelf from <hi>Rocheſter</hi> about <hi>One</hi> in the Morning.) And to this you may add, That the expoſing her Corps to publick View, and lying in State, happens to be in the ſame Month of <hi>February,</hi> in which ſhe and her Husband were proclaimed in <hi>publick</hi> King and Queen: And to compleat the Parallel, One great Reaſon, if not the only Reaſon of the delay to this Month was, for that the <hi>Purple</hi> (the Royal Colours) to adorn the Solemnity was expected from <hi>Holland.</hi> And I doubt not but a critical and curious Obſerver will find, That every remarkable Moment in her Sickneſs, Death, Funeral Pomp, and Funeral it ſelf, will anſwer to ſo many ſeveral Steps made in the Revolution. How far ſuch Things as theſe are Argumentative, either from the Nature of Things, the Obſervations of Men, or the ordinary Methods of Divine Providences, I ſhall not now enquire: Only I am certain, This is <hi>Argumentum ad Hominem;</hi> and theſe Gentlemen who have uſed it themſelves, and with ſuch great Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance too, can never Except againſt it. For if <hi>Years,</hi> and <hi>Seaſons of the Year,</hi> and ſuch like, are Things ſo obſervable, as from thence to point out a Determination of the Divine Will, or to ſignify God's Approbation or Diſlike, here we have them all, even to <hi>Months</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:59293:29"/>
and <hi>Hours,</hi> with an Accumulation of Circumſtances; and their own Arguments turn upon them with this great Advantage, That for <hi>Days</hi> in which Men are to perform any remarkable Actions, they are frequently in their own Choice, and <hi>Fataliſts</hi> (who are Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Obſervers of Times and Seaſons) will be ſure to pitch upon ſuch Days as they think, or have obſerv'd to be fortunate to them: But <hi>Death</hi> is out of our Choice and Power, 'tis the peculiar Stroke of God himſelf. <hi>Cromwel</hi> gain'd two famous and fortunate Victories on the 3d of <hi>Sept.</hi> but he died on that Day too, and all his Hopes were blaſted, and an End put to his <hi>Uſurpation;</hi> which not only eternally confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the bold and blaſphemous Arguments drawn <hi>for him</hi> from Providence and Succeſs, but turn'd the Edge of them directly upon themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The laſt Thing I ſhall obſerve to you, is, The Excurſion the Doctor makes in Memory of an <hi>old Friend</hi> of his (p. 16. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>) This <hi>old Friend</hi> you muſt know is Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> between whom and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, it ſeems, were very great Endearments; although after the Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution there might be for ſome time a Miſunderſtanding, which the Doctor out of his Generoſity can forget (and if other People would forget it too, it would never be the worſe for him:) But even at the ſame time the diſtance was not ſo wide as ſome People thought; for there was another <hi>Friend</hi> of his, and who was <hi>Friend</hi> to them both, who all along kept up the Amity and Correſpondence; and you know the Maxim, <hi>Quae conveniunt in aliquo tertio, conveniunt inter ſe:</hi> So that it might be <hi>old Friendſhip</hi> ſtill, notwithſtanding the outward ſeeming and apearance to the contrary. Well, Friendſhip or no Friendſhip, Old or New, the Doctor however hath abundance of fine Words to ſay, and they are but Words; for there is no Truth, nor colour of Truth in the bottom, but that I ſuppoſe may be excuſed, if there is a Friend in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Place the Doctor tells us, <hi>He had great Deſigns to ſerve the Chriſtian Religion, and the Church of</hi> England <hi>in its trueſt Intereſts.</hi> And again, <hi>The great uſe he made of the Favour and Intereſt that he had, was to do publick Service to Religion, and whatever ſome Men might ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, to the Church of</hi> England. Well then it ſeems this Matter was not ſo clear, but there were ſome <hi>Suſpicions</hi> as to his Deſigns on this Head: And the ſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Queſtion is, Whether theſe <hi>Suſpicions</hi> were juſt and reaſonable? As for that, the Doctor leaves People to think as they pleaſe, and hath not ſaid one Word to diſcharge them, but plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirms them: For he adds immediately, <hi>though it may not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly in their way.</hi> Now the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as it ſuſtains that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59293:30"/>
ſtands diſtinguiſhed from Diſſenters of all Sorts by her <hi>Canons Articles, Homilies,</hi> and <hi>Liturgy;</hi> and the <hi>old Way</hi> of purſuing the <hi>Churches Intereſt</hi> was by being true to theſe our ſelves, and by uſing our Power and Authority that others might be ſo too. And this is the way that hithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to hath been taken, by all thoſe who have heartily and honeſtly eſpouſed the Intereſt of the Church, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reformation. But this was a <hi>Way</hi> that did not pleaſe the Doctor's <hi>Friend</hi> but he was for a <hi>new Way</hi> of his own; and though the Doctor does not tell us what <hi>Way</hi> that was, it was ſufficiently known, It was a <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>Alteration</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> and he made a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner for that Purpoſe, and would fain have been <hi>Prolocutor</hi> of the Convocation to have brought it to effect. And this was that <hi>great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> he was always purſuing with all his Might and Cunning; that is, He was endeavo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to alter and comprehend away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Church, who being himſelf firſt falſe to her Principles and Conſtitution, was deſigning to frame a Church of the ſame Model, and make it as falſe as himſelf In ſhort, he was for making a <hi>Dutch Church</hi> of an <hi>Engliſh one,</hi> which is a very fine way indeed of having <hi>Deſigns to ſerve the Church of</hi> England <hi>in its trueſt Intereſts:</hi> I doubt not but Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and another of the Doctor's <hi>old Friends,</hi> Dr <hi>J. O.</hi> had alſo great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to ſerve the Church of <hi>England though not perfectly in their Way;</hi> that is, In a Way to let themſelves and their Schiſm into the Church, which is Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Way. So that had the Doctor ſaid, That his <hi>old Friend</hi> had great Deſigns for the Intereſt of the Diſſenters, he had ſpoke truth; and I dare ſay he will yet ſay it, if ever Things be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipe enough to open thus boldly. But to talk of his Deſigns for the trueſt Intereſts of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> 'tis the extravaganteſt Thing in the World: For there is nothing more ridiculous, than to call thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns for the <hi>Church of England</hi> which were deſigned purely to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it; to throw up the Incloſure and make it <hi>Common;</hi> to take away thoſe Things upon the Account of which it hath its denomination, and is diſtinguiſhed from all others, and particularly the Doctor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Friends</hi> the <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> But I had rather you ſhould have this in Dr <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s own Words, and you ſhall ſee what he hath ſaid and printed of this <hi>very Man,</hi> and in this <hi>very Caſe.</hi> And in the firſt Place he enquires whether there is any Neceſſity of ſuch Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, and ſays,<note n="*">A Letter concerning ſome Querys about the new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for the making Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in the Liturgy, Canons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Members of the Church of</hi> England <hi>generally believe there is none.</hi> And then asks, <hi>Whether it be for the Reputation and Eſtabliſhment of the Church, or for the Increaſe of Reverence and Devotion in the People, to be ſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59293:30"/>
frequently meditating unneceſſary Alterations?</hi> Again he asks, <hi>Whether it be for the Peace, Unity, and Edification of the Church, for ſome few aſſuming Men to alter the eſtabliſh'd Worſhip, to make it comply with their own private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, or to ſerve their own private Ends? Whether it be for the Churches Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to change the ancient Rules and Forms of Worſhip for ſome new mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Inventions? How ſhall we juſtify our ſelves againſt the Charge of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty and Innovation, if we reform away all the Remains and Characters of a Primitive and Apoſtolick Church?</hi> Here you have Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Notion of the <hi>Deſign,</hi> and there is much more to the ſame Purpoſe. And now you ſhall have his Opinion of the Man in the purſuit of this <hi>Deſign; Whether the known Character of ſome leading Men in this Commiſſion be not Reaſon enough to ſuſpect the Event? Whether Men who conform'd with dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty themſelves, or upon Principles which wiſe Men foreſaw would deſtroy the Church in time, who have Latitude to conform to a Church</hi> de Facto, <hi>which hath Power on its Side, and to conceal their own Inclinations till it is time to ſhew them are not likely to do the Church of</hi> England <hi>a good Turn when opportunity ſerves, and which perhaps they imagine now they have?</hi> Again, <hi>Whether there was any ſuch haſte of altering the beſt conſtituted Church in the World, which honourable Title ſome of theſe Commiſſioners in a good Mood, have in their Writings beſtowed upon the Church of</hi> England? Meaning his old Friend Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> Once again, <hi>And thus our Church may be changed, and altered, and transformed by Nine Men, who may have Tenderneſs and Moderation enough to part with any Thing but their Church Preferments.</hi> Now, Sir, you will confeſs that the Doctor t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eats his <hi>Friend,</hi> eſpecially an <hi>old Friend,</hi> a little courſely and unfriendly. And I doubt very much whether the Doctor in thoſe days would have given him <hi>his Vote</hi> for the <hi>Archbiſhoprick,</hi> or yet for the following Characters, <hi>of the cleareſt and brighteſt Reaſon, truer, Judgment, more inflexible fearleſs Honeſty;</hi> for theſe are directly contrary to the Characters he gives of him here. But the Doctor I ſuppoſe is grown <hi>Wiſer</hi> now, and which you know <hi>no Man is forbid.</hi> Nay, he is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>own <hi>wiſer</hi> than the <hi>wiſe Men</hi> themſelves; for you have heard, That <hi>wiſe Men foreſaw ſuch Principles would deſtroy the Church in time.</hi> But the Doctor now is ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> as to ſee plain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, That thoſe Principles are for the Churches <hi>trueſt Intereſts.</hi> Now, Sir, whatever you may think of the Cauſe, I pray now tell me what you think of the <hi>Preacher?</hi> Are not theſe delicate Things from the Mouth of Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> who hath in ſo many Words aſſerted the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ean contrary of the <hi>ſame Deſign,</hi> and of the <hi>ſame Man</hi> engag'd in that <hi>Deſign?</hi> Had the Doctor nothing to ſay for his <hi>old Friend,</hi> but by ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his own Face and ſhewing himſelf to the World for a <hi>rank Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> in contradicting almoſt every Thing that ever he ſaid in his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59293:31"/>
whole Life; in the mean time he may <hi>ſay</hi> and <hi>preach</hi> what he pleaſe of this, or of any other Perſon, but he hath taken extraordiny Care that no Body ſhould believe him: For if Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Character is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon the Credit of Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> then you muſt believe <hi>both</hi> or <hi>none;</hi> for the <hi>Queries</hi> and the <hi>Sermon</hi> have the <hi>ſame Author,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> too: However at laſt it was Friendly done, to ſacrifice his own Reputation to the Memory of his Friend. For by contradicting the <hi>hard and foul</hi> Characters he has given of Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> he hath taken off the Credit of them, ſo far as they relate to him, and no Man is bound to believe them becauſe Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſaid them; but his Friend's Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will get but little by the Bargain, for this taints all his good Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters too, and for the ſame Reaſon no Body is bound to believe them. Here we have of the ſame Perſon, upon the the ſame Occaſion, and by the ſelf-ſame Man, theſe very agreeing Characters, That he had, and he had not, good Inclinations to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> That his Deſigns were, and they were not, for the Reputation of that Church; That <hi>whatever ſome might ſuſpect,</hi> he did, and he did not, purpoſe to ſerve her in her <hi>trueſt Intereſts,</hi> That he was, and was not, a Time-ſerver; Did, and did not, conceal his <hi>Inclinations</hi> to do the Church a good Turn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the preſent Age and Poſterity is left to believe which they pleaſe, either or neither; for what Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſays on one Side, the ſame Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> confutes on the other. So that whether the Doctor hath conſulted his Friend's Reputation, it is plain he forgot his own: For ſuch changeable and double dealing in matters of ſuch Moment hath been always infamous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſay no worſe. And the Doctor ſtands upon Record, both as to <hi>Perſons, Things,</hi> and <hi>Cauſes,</hi> the greateſt Inſtance of <hi>Self-contradiction,</hi> that this, or perhaps any other Age hath bred.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with a large Reflexion on his other Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for a very few Words will ſerve the turn, and the very naming them is ſufficient to expoſe them. In the next Place he tells you, <hi>The greateſt Fault I know he had, was, That ſome Envious and Ambitious Men could not bear his Greatneſs, which he himſelf never Courted, nay, which he induſtriouſly Avoided.</hi> This you muſt take for a Commendation of his ſingular <hi>Modeſty,</hi> join'd with an Aſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion of <hi>Envy</hi> upon ſome others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I doubt neither of them very true: So whether he <hi>courted</hi> his Greatneſs or no, a very little <hi>Induſtry</hi> would have ſerved to <hi>avoid</hi> it. And any Man who knows the Methods uſed for the gaining Poſſeſſion of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> will be ſoon ſatisfied, That though there was very little <hi>Courtſhip,</hi> there was a great deal of <hi>Induſtry</hi> imployed: And it is very pleaſant to talk of ſuch a Man <hi>induſtriouſly Avoiding,</hi> when he was not only an <hi>Intruder,</hi> but violently <hi>thruſt</hi> himſelf into another Prelate's
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59293:31"/>
Right, by litigious Suits, and falſe Claims, and under the pretended Power of Law. And then for his <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> it carried its Antidote with it, and there was enough to choke any Man's Appetite, whoſe Ambition did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed his Probity: For he was both an <hi>Uſurper</hi>'s and an <hi>uſurping</hi> Biſhop. And theſe are no ſuch tempting Titles and Acquiſitions, as to move the Envy of any, but ſuch as Dr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi> And I doubt I cannot ſo ſafely apply the remaining part of the Character to the Doctor, as I did ſome before, <hi>(viz.) That he never Courted, but induſtriouſly Avoided</hi> his Preferments. And then it will follow, That thoſe <hi>who induſtriously Court</hi> Preferments, are the <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious</hi> Men who <hi>envied</hi> his Greatneſs. And by this <hi>Mark</hi> the Doctor, if he pleaſes may diſtinguiſh them, and point them out; for I dare ſay, There is never a <hi>true</hi> Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who <hi>envied</hi> his Greatneſs, but deſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed it; and whomſoever he would inſinuate by this g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, 'tis as plain as the Sun, That it ſuits with no Body but themſelves.</p>
            <p>The next Thing is very fine and Artificial; <hi>Had it been put to the Poll there would have been vaſt Odds on his Side, that he would have been voted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the See of</hi> Canterbury. You ſee the Doctor's Rhetorick runs very low, when he is forc'd to take up with ſuch Childiſh Topicks. 'Tis an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Vertue indeed that muſt receive its Luſtre from the <hi>Poll;</hi> and the Doctor hath given us a curious Rule by which to meaſure <hi>worth, (viz) The Mob and moſt Voices.</hi> In the mean time this Aſſertion is as <hi>bold</hi> as 'tis <hi>ridiculous:</hi> The Doctor would be thought a wiſe Man, as if he had felt the Pulſe of the whole Kingdom, and knew well the Inclinations of all the People; for he tells us, <hi>All</hi> England <hi>knew his worth:</hi> Whereas this plainly betrays him, and ſhews, That though he talks large and wide, and like a Traveller, yet that in truth he was bred at home, and knows very little beyond his own Doors. For above one half of the People ſcarcely ſo much as heard of his Name, and four parts of ſix hardly knew whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had any Worth or no; whether he was good for ſomething, or for nothing: And of thoſe who did know him, a great many knew him a little too well to give their Vote for him. And of this we have a very plain and full Inſtance; when he ſtood to be <hi>Prolocutor</hi> of the <hi>Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> there was as undecent and uncanonical Strugling to make a Party for him, as perhaps ever was known in <hi>England;</hi> and yet neither his <hi>own worth</hi> (ſo great and ſo known as the Doctor ſays) nor the Intereſt and Canvaſing of Dr. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and all the <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> Tribe with all the Wilt, Cunning, Vigilance and Artifice, were able to carry it; but all the <hi>Odds</hi> was againſt him, and that conſiderably. So that, I doubt, the Doctor is a little out, as to his Judgment about the <hi>Poll.</hi> In the mean time, it is very pleaſant to talk of <hi>Voting</hi> an Archbiſhop into the See of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> as if the <hi>Mob,</hi> and vulgar Multitude (by far the moſt numerous of any Nation) were the fitteſt Judges of Epiſcopal Qualifications: And ſee what a wiſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59293:32"/>
Reaſon he gives for this, <hi>For no Man had ever a clearer and brighter Reaſon; a truer Judgment, a more eaſy and happy Expreſſion, nor a more inflexible fearleſs Honeſty.</hi> Now that Particle, <hi>For,</hi> denotes the Reaſon why the <hi>vaſt Odds in Polling would have been on his Side;</hi> and therefore you muſt needs be convinc'd that he would certainly have carried it, becauſe the common People are the beſt J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dges in the World of <hi>clear and bright Reaſon, true Judgment, happy Expreſſion, and fearleſs Honeſty.</hi> He had better by half have mention'd his Corpulency and Fatneſs, or his Hoſpitality (if he cou'd have told how) or any Thing elſe for a Reaſon, and the People would have <hi>voted</hi> him into <hi>Canterbury,</hi> becauſe he was Plump, and Well-liking, and Fatter than other People, and then the Reaſon would have ſuited the Subject; for they are a thouſand times bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Judges of this, than of <hi>Reaſon, Judgment,</hi> or <hi>Expreſſions.</hi> But now the Reaſon is more ridiculous than the Aſſertion. 'Tis extream Folly to diſtinguiſh a Man's Vertue by the Odds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Polling, and Voting; but it is ten times more ſo, to give that as a Reaſon, which not one in a thouſand of the <hi>Voters</hi> underſtand any Thing of. In the mean time, if this be the only Reaſon (and the Doctor aſſigns this and no other) why he thinks he would have been <hi>voted</hi> into the <hi>Metropolitical See<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I hope thoſe who underſtand what is <hi>clear Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>true Judgment,</hi> will be allowed the fitteſt Judges and moſt competent Electors; and then I doubt inſtead of being <hi>voted in,</hi> he would have been <hi>voted out.</hi> For in the Inſtance before, a <hi>Convocation</hi> of learned Divines, who well underſtood theſe Qualities, and were very able to Judg of them, <hi>voted</hi> directly againſt him: So that if theſe <hi>clear bright,</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> Things of <hi>Reaſon, Judgment</hi> and <hi>Expreſſion,</hi> are to be meaſur'd by <hi>Vote,</hi> the Doctor hath plainly loſt his Cauſe; for in ſuch Caſes the Vote of learned Men, and of the ſame Profeſſion, is far mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e conſiderable than that of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if there had been any ſuch Thing. But the Doctor's <hi>Votes</hi> are <hi>Votes</hi> in Dream and Fancy, and he celebrates his Fiend's Memory by Chimera's, and nothing; and not only ſo but in plain Oppoſition to Things really in being: And I hope one <hi>actual</hi> Vote preponderates, and is of more worth than ten thouſand of the Doctor's <hi>imaginary</hi> ones.</p>
            <p>Next to, his <hi>clear and bright Reaſon,</hi> &amp;c. the Doctor celebrates his willingneſs to <hi>forgive,</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>He could eaſily forgive an Enemy, as that Bundle of Libels witneſſes which was found among his other Papers, with this Inſcription; Theſe are Libels, I pray God forgive them I do.</hi> Now as to this Character, I do not know whether the Doctor would ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it to the <hi>Poll</hi> as he does his <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judgment;</hi> but if he would, I doubt there are ſome Living who could honeſtly <hi>Vote</hi> the contrary: And particularly the <hi>Chriſt-church</hi> Men, whom he always eſteem'd and treated as Enemies to the day of his Death, for no other Reaſon, that ever I could hear, or I believe the Doctor can tell, but that ſome of that <hi>College</hi> acted
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59293:32"/>
according to the beſt of their Judgment, and preferr'd before him a more fit Perſon of their own Body to be Prolocutor of the Convocation. In the mean time this is too great a Vertue to be hudled up in <hi>Generals,</hi> and left to the ſingle Teſtimony of a Poſthumous Inſcription upon ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Papers. Does the Doctor know any one Inſtance of a Perſon who bore him ill Will, or actually provoked him, or highly diſobliged him, whom notwithſtanding he repaid with favour and kindneſs, and <hi>heap'd Coals of Fire upon his Head.</hi> The Doctor tell us, he was his <hi>Friend,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently muſt be acquainted with ſome of the <hi>ſecret,</hi> as well as the <hi>open</hi> Paſſages of his Life, and if he had known any Thing of this, to be ſure we ſhould have heard of it; but to talk ſo magnificently of his <hi>eaſineſs of forgiving Enemies,</hi> and have nothing at all to ſay for it, but the Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a blind Bundle, which no Body knows the Contents of, is a groſs impoſition on his Hearers: However as to <hi>Libels,</hi> I muſt confeſs there was a ſevere <hi>Libel</hi> writ againſt him, the Title of which is, <hi>A Letter to the Lord Ruſſel,</hi> the Author Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> and this indeed <hi>Libels</hi> and reproaches him, far beyond what his moſt malicious Enemies were ever able to do. And theſe Gentlemen had need talk of <hi>Libels,</hi> when they have taken ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Pains to <hi>Libel</hi> themſelves. Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi>'s <hi>Paraphraſes</hi> are a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious <hi>Libel</hi> againſt him; and Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Jeſuits Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi> is a terrible <hi>Libel</hi> againſt him; and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s <hi>Caſe of Reſiſtance,</hi> and all his <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> before the <hi>Oath,</hi> are venomous and inveterate <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> againſt him, and againſt all that he hath preached and written ſince. Theſe are <hi>Libels,</hi> and perpetual <hi>Libels,</hi> and will remain everlaſting Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Infamy, except they can perſwade the People to burn all their <hi>Books,</hi> and forget all their <hi>Sermons.</hi> So that (to give theſe Gentlemen their due) they have ſav'd their Adverſaries all the trouble in this Point, and (whatever they may think on't) they have ſomething elſe to do, than to beat ſo common and trite an Argument, to trouble the World with any more <hi>Libels</hi> upon them, when they find ſo many already made to their hands by the Gentlemen themſelves.</p>
            <p>And thus, Sir, I have made an End of the Task which you have impos'd on me; I ſhall take my leave of you with this Advice from the whole, That if you purpoſe when you are called from the World to have the Solemnity of your Interment graced with a <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> that you will give direction that the <hi>Preacher</hi> be a Man of <hi>Probity</hi> and <hi>Principles;</hi> for otherwiſe no Man will believe your Vertues upon the Credit of your <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator,</hi> and your Memory may be blaſted inſtead of being recommended: For let him ſay never ſo many good Things of you, it is not impoſſible but before the Year comes about, he may <hi>recant</hi> and <hi>renounce</hi> every Word of it.</p>
            <p>Before I conclude, I think my ſelf ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig'd (in this ſecond Letter) to account to you for declining Compliance with your new Requeſt, of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marking
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59293:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
on Dr.</hi> Payn<hi>'s Sermon</hi> on the ſame Subject. Your Intimation made me undertake the Penance of reading ſome of it; but to go through it, is too great a Diſcipline for any Man, whoſe Palate hath ever reliſh'd any Thing above <hi>three half Penny Poetry.</hi> Why, Sir, many Years ago I have heard ſome of it ſung about the Streets in wretched and nauſeous <hi>Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerel.</hi> What do you think of this? p. 6. <hi>I know not how to draw her Picture, 'tis ſo all over Beauteous without any Foil, any Shade, any Blemiſh; ſo perfect in every Feature, ſo accompliſht in every Part, ſo adorn'd with every Perfection and every Grace.</hi> O Rare, Sir! Here's <hi>Phillis and Chloris, and Jilliana Croyden.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Sh' hath <hi>every Feature, every Grace;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So charming <hi>every Part</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
'Tis no wonder he tells us, (p. 8.) of <hi>ſtrewing her with the Flowers of withered and decayed Poetry;</hi> for the <hi>Song</hi> out of which he hath tranſcribed his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> is of very <hi>great Age,</hi> and hath been <hi>ſung</hi> at many a <hi>Whitſun Ale,</hi> and many a <hi>Wedding,</hi> (though I believe never at a <hi>Funeral</hi> before) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all this time may very well be <hi>decay'd and wither'd:</hi> In the mean time, if you, Sir, were to draw the <hi>Picture</hi> of a <hi>great Princeſs,</hi> I fancy you would not make choice of <hi>Mopſa</hi> to ſit for it. Alas! Sir, there was <hi>Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> and many a fam'd <hi>Romance</hi> more, which migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have furniſht him with handſom Characters, and yet he muſt needs be <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and inſtructing</hi> his People out of <hi>Hey down derry,</hi> and <hi>the fair Maid of Kent.</hi> If he had intitled it, <hi>the White Chappel Ballad,</hi> and got ſome Body to ſet it to the Tune of <hi>Amarillis,</hi> compoſed by <hi>W.P. Songſter,</hi> the Character of the <hi>Author,</hi> the <hi>Title,</hi> and the <hi>Matter,</hi> would have very well agreed, and perhaps it might have paſſed at the Corners of Streets; but to call it a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and by <hi>W.P. Doctor</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> 'tis one of the <hi>lewdeſt</hi> Things in the World. It may be reckon'd among the Misfortunes of this Princeſs, that <hi>her Memory</hi> is celebrated in the <hi>Language</hi> of the <hi>Stews;</hi> her Fame told in the <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Dialect</hi> wherewith the <hi>Beauxs</hi> ſerenade their <hi>Miſſes.</hi> And the <hi>Place</hi> from whence it comes will never mend it; for though the <hi>Pulpit</hi> of late Years hath done Wonders, and made the ſame Things <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Wrong, True</hi> and <hi>Falſe;</hi> yet I think it will hardly undertake to elevate <hi>Gru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtreet</hi> among the <hi>Muſes,</hi> to tranſlate a <hi>looſe unſavory,</hi> and <hi>slovenly Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lad,</hi> into <hi>Hymns</hi> and <hi>decent Praiſes.</hi> However, if <hi>they</hi> think ſuch Things ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Gravity</hi> of their Character, they may enjoy their Humour for me: I think it much below mine, to <hi>beſmear</hi> my ſelf in taking notice of it. And (I pray pardon my Reſentment) I am ſorry you think your poor Friend hath nothing elſe to do, than to make <hi>Remarks</hi> on <hi>Fa la la,</hi> and <hi>Lilly Bollero;</hi> let it be <hi>preach'd</hi> where it will, and call'd by what Name they pleaſe. I am, Sir, yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
